<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="132"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[TABLE OF CONTENTS

          UNIT 1

Lesson 1              SOURCES OF OUR FAITH
Lesson 2
Lesson 3  We Learn About God in the Wonders of Natures...............3
Lesson 4  God’s Gift to Adam andt Eve.............................................12
Lesson 5  God Spoke to Abraham ......................................................20
          God Speaks Through the Scripture.....................................29
          We Know Jesus Through the Bible.......................................36

                UNIT 2

                        WE PROFESS OUR FAITH

Lesson 6 We Believe in God the Father.............................................45
Lesson 7 Jesus Tells Us About His Father.............................................54
Lesson 8 The Holy Spirit Lives In Us.......................................................61
Lesson 9 The Christian Community of Believers................................67
Lesson 10 Mary, Mother of Christ..........................................................74
Lesson 11 We Honor Mary.....................................................................81]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[UNIT 3

           WE LIVE OUR FAITH

Lesson 12 Jesus, Our Friend..................................................................93

Lesson 13 We are Active Members of the Church.........................100

Lesson 14  We Become Close to God Through
           His Commandments.........................................................107
Lesson 15  We Help from the Heart ...................................................114
Lesson 16  We Are Sent to Serve........................................................122
Lesson 17  We Become Members of the Church ............................129
Lesson 18  God’s Call to Everyone.....................................................135

           UNIT 4

           WE CELEBRATE OUR FAITH

Lesson 19 We Share God’s Words to Others....................................143
Lesson 20 Jesus Accepts a Repentant Heart..................................150
Lesson 21 Jesus is Present in the Holy Eucharist...............................157
Lesson 22 Jesus Gathers Us Together at Holy Mass.........................164
Lesson 23 We Humbly Pray to God...................................................172
Lesson 24 We Must Pray Everyday....................................................179

    SPECIAL LESSONS

Lesson 25 The Greatest Gift to Everyone.........................................189
Lesson 26 The Spirit of Jesus in Marie Rivier......................................197]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[UNIT 1

SOURCES OF OUR FAITH

                               God’s Presence in His Creation]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[SOURCES OF OUR FAITH

       This unit focuses on the Revelation of God, Sacred Tradition and
Sacred Scripture. The learners are introduced to the Sources of Faith of
the Catholic Church. They gradually become convinced that Sacred
Tradition is not the only way to know God for their holiness and salvation.
This is a great treasure of the Church that must be adhered to and kept.
The learners are introduced to read and understand the Sacred Scripture
as God’s Word speaking to them. The learners also need to know and
understand the basic teachings of the Church and how these apply in
their lives.

 The Author
    Marie
    Rivier,
   Woman
   Apostle]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Lesson God in the Wonders of

We Natures

Learn               1
About

Expected Outcomes:

a. To tell that God is powerful, God is wise, God is love.

b. To see and praise God in His creation.

c. To pray and thank God for His wonderful creation.

Life Situation

Do you still remember the poem that you learned when you were in

Grade One or in Grade Two? Everybody recite this poem:

                       Twinkle, Twinkle little stars
                       How I wonder what you are
                       Up above the world so high
                       Like the diamond in the sky.
                       Twinkle, Twinkle little stars
                       How I wonder what you are.

Everybody knows the tune of this song.
Let us sing together.]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Now let us go out and look around. There are many things that we
see around us that are God’s creation. What are they? Describe each
one.
1. Draw them inside the circle.
2. Color only the things made by God.]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Values Development

       Every time you look at the sky, you should think of someone’s name.
Give three guesses. Write them on the blanks below.
_______________________________________________________________________
_______________________________________________________________________
________________________________________________________

Why should we think of God’s name when we look at the sky?

Who created all these stars? Stars are like big world themselves.

Why do so many big stars crash? Does it tell us how wise God is?

What makes the world beautiful?

       What happens if there are no people around who will take care of
the wonders of God?]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Proclamation of the Word of God

    In the beginning, when God created the heavens and the earth,
the earth was a formless wasteland, and darkness covered the abyss,
while a mighty wind swept over the water. Then God said, “Let there
be light”, and there was light, God saw how good the light was.
Then, God said, “Let there be a dome in the middle of the waters,” to
separate one body of water from the others. And so it happened.
Then God said, “Let the water under the sky be gathered into a single
basin, so that the dry land may appear.” God called the dry land
“the earth” and the basin of the water be called “the sea”. Then
God said, “Let the earth bring forth vegetation: every kind of plant
that bears seed and every kind of fruit tree on earth that bears fruit
with its seed in it.” Then God said: “Let there be lights in the sky to
shed lights upon the earth.” God made the two great lights, the one
to govern the day and the lesser one to govern the night; and He
made the stars. Then God said, “Let the water teem with an
abundance of living creatures, let birds fly.” So, God created the great
sea monsters and all kinds of swimming creatures with which the water
teems and all kinds of winged birds. God blessed them, saying, “Be
fertile, multiply and fill the water of the seas and let the birds multiply
on the earth.” Then God said, “Let the earth bring forth all kinds of
living creatures: cattle, creeping things, and wild animals of all kinds.”
God made all kinds of wild animals, all kinds of cattle,]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[and all kinds of creeping things of the earth. God saw how good it
  was. Then God said, “Let us make man in our image, after our
  likeness. Let them have dominion over the fish of the sea, the birds of
  the air, and the cattle, and over all the wild animals and all the
  creatures that crawl on the ground.”

                                                                                                          Genesis 1: 1- 31

Knowing our Faith

       We know that God is great. He has made more stars that we
cannot count.

       The astronomers who study the sky tell us that there are about as
many stars as there are grains of the sand on all the seashores of all the
earth.

       God has made laws to keep the stars on a safe track. These laws
tell us that God is wise. God is powerful. God is perfect. God is love.
We see His wisdom, power, goodness, beauty, love and holiness in the
things around us.

                                                                                                                    CCC 65, 67]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Challenges of our Faith

       When we see space films or read about astronaut adventures, who
do we think about? To whom does space belong? When men find out
more about space, whose secrets are they discovering?
As we learn more about God from space, what could we say to Him?

       We can praise our Heavenly Father as He is greater, more powerful,
wiser than all earthly fathers. We cannot do what God can do.

Enhancing our Faith

       Our Heavenly Father is a great, wise, and loving God. When we look
up the sky at night, the twinkling stars seem very small. But many of the
stars and planets are much bigger than the earth.

       When we learn about the wonders of God’s world, we praise
God because everything comes from Him. When we enjoy our food we
know God loves us. When we see a beautiful scene, we know God is
beautiful. When we see and hear the great deep sea, we know God is
strong. When we see living things grow, we know that God is wise and
powerful.]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Art It Out
Show that God is wise and powerful. Color your drawing.]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Living our Faith

       God also loves us when we feel His loving arms around us especially
when we are with our parents, brothers, sisters, friends and elders.

       We praise God for the wonders of His creation by seeing all these
wonderful things around us. Like our mother, she realized that her
children loved her and we can see how much God loves us through her.

       We also show our love to our parents, brothers and sisters by
respecting and obeying them. We recognize in them the presence and
love of God because we know that all of us are the wonders of God.

Celebrating our Faith

       Let us pray and thank God for the many things we see as signs of
God in making Himself known to us.

Group I                        Group II

All things the Lord has made.  - we praise and bless you, Lord
                                      - we praise and bless you,
- Powers of the Lord!
Lord

- Sun and Moon!                - we praise and bless you,
    Bless the Lord

Lord

- Stars of Heaven!             - we praise and bless you,

    Bless the Lord
Lord]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[- Mountains and hills!           - we praise and bless you, Lord
    Bless the Lord               - we praise and bless you, Lord
                                 - we praise and bless you, Lord
- All you lovely gifts to us
                                 - we praise and bless you, Lord
- All the birds that

    sweetly sings

- All the fish that
    smoothly swims

- All flowers that bloom         - we praise and bless you, Lord
    about our feet

- For tasty food we eat          - we praise and bless you, Lord

- For parents, brothers,                 - we praise and bless you,
    sisters and all friends

Lord

- Give thanks to the                     - we praise and bless

                   you,

                   Lord for He is good.              Lord for

                   your love is

                                 everlasting, Amen.

Message from Marie Rivier

My dear children,

         This divine Word, this Bread of Life is in your mouths and in your hearts, my dear
ones: it seems to me that he cannot come close than that.]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Lesson Gift to Adam and Eve

  2

 God’s

Expected Outcomes:
a. To identify the gifts of God to Adam and Eve.
b. To appreciate God’s gifts of life and love.
c. To say a prayer thanking God for the gifts of life and love.

Life Situation

       Read a short story below how the children appreciate the gifts
given by their parents.

                                      Gifts are Signs of Love

       A
Grade Three
teacher, Mrs. Angeles asked her pupils to describe the members of their
family. Faith shared that her father goes to work everyday to earn a
living for the members of their family.

       Another pupil, Hope told her classmates that every weekend her
father and mother would bring them at the malls for shopping and
sometimes buy new clothes and shoes as their gifts. Almost all the pupils
of Mrs. Angeles shared how their parents love them.]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Everybody praised their family for the gifts they received every day
especially for the love of their father and mother to each one in the
family.

Values Development

       Does your father give special care for you? Does your mother show
her love and care for you? What are the things they give you?

       If you look around, try to point out to us the things that make you
happy. You can see the beautiful things made by God. All living things
around us are all gifts from God. They are all beautiful.

       What are the most wonderful and useful things that you enjoy with?
All fruits and vegetables were made by God for our food.

       What else? He made the birds for us. He made the fish and
animals. But the most wonderful gift is our parents. Through them we
receive the gifts of life and love. What happens if we do not have
parents? Do you want to know more what God had made for us? In
what way did God share His life and love for us?]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Proclamation of the Word of God

     At that time God made man out of dust from the soil, then He
breathed into his nostrils a breath of life and he became a man,
named Adam and placed him in the garden of Eden or Paradise. He
said that it is not good that the man should be alone so when the man
was asleep, he took one of his ribs and enclosed it in flesh. God built
up the rib he had taken from the man into a woman and brought her
to the man. Now both of them were naked, the man and his wife, but
they felt no shame in front of each other. There was a serpent in the
garden the most subtle of all the wild animals that God had made. It
asked the woman, “Did God really say you were not to eat from any of
the trees in the garden?” The woman named Eve answered. “We
may eat of the fruit of the trees in the garden.” It is only about the fruit
of the tree in the middle of the garden that God said: “ You shall not
eat or even touch it.” The serpent said, “You will not die.” But Eve
saw that the fruit of the tree was good to eat, she took some and ate
it. She gave some to her husband, Adam. They heard God walking
but they hid themselves. God called for them, “Where are you?”
God expelled them from the garden of paradise.

                                                                                                 Genesis 2: 7-23;3:1-7]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Knowing our Faith

       God our Father showed His great love to Adam and Eve. They were
the first man and woman who belonged to God. He prepared the
earth for them. God showed His power, wisdom and love and for
everyone to use it and enjoy it. With their body they used and enjoyed
God’s gifts. The animals God made could see, hear and taste also. But
God gave to people a soul as well as a body, a soul made in the likeness
of God.

       Adam and Eve could know and love God their Father, could listen

to His orders and could understand His plans for them. They knew that
God made the world to show his power, wisdom and love. God gave
them a soul and body so that they could know and love Him and use
and enjoy His gifts. In His great love God gave them much more than His
plan for them so that they would always have happiness.]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Challenges of our Faith

       It is true that God wants us to be happy always but God still gave us
wonderful gifts more than this. In His great love, God wants us to live
with Him forever. So that we could do what God wants us to share in His
own life and love. This is called the life of grace.

       But sometimes God tested us especially when we don’t listen to

anybody. Like in the life of Adam and Eve. They did not obey God, they
committed sin. Adam and Eve turned away from God’s love. They lost
this important gift, a share in God’s life and love. They were punished
from their sin. However, Adam and Eve could still think, know and love
God and they could still choose. They were sorry for their sin.]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Enhancing our Faith

       God’s plan was that Adam and Eve would live with Him forever and
be happier than we could imagine.

A. Recall the gifts God gave to Adam and Eve:
     1. _____________________________
     2. _____________________________

B. Make a list of other wonderful gifts which God gave to Adam and
     Eve that made them happy.
       a._________________ e. ________________
       b._________________ f. ________________
       c._________________ g. ________________
       d._________________ h. ________________

C. Draw the picture of Adam and Eve which shows that they are happy
     in the Garden of Eden.]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Living our Faith

       Adam and Eve committed a serious sin and offended God. They
tried to hide from God but God sees them always. They no longer had
happiness. They still lived in this beautiful world but not in the Garden of
Paradise.

       God has given us also a beautiful world. He gave us gifts of body
and soul. He wants us to use His gifts and enjoy them. We also have
the power to choose.

       We should pray every day and stay close to God by being
obedient children at home to our parents and members of our family.
We also follow the rules and abide with the laws and regulations in
school given by our teachers and other people of the Church.]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Celebrating our Faith

       Our Heavenly Father, we are sorry for our sins. You are always
ready to give us another chance. We are aware that you know what to
do for us. You promised to send us a Savior who would show us the way
back to You. You have shown us your merciful love. As a loving
Father, You can grant us mercy because of your love for us is great.

Let us all say:

       Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit. As it
was in the beginning is now and ever shall be world without end. Amen.

       Let us pray for the repentance of sinners and for our conversion as
we say together the Act of Contrition.

O my God, I am heartily sorry for having offended You…

Message from Marie Rivier

My dear children,

       Christ Jesus wants us to make him known and loved to bring him
wherever Divine Providence calls us.]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Lesson  Spoke to Abraham

  God         3

Expected Outcomes:
a. To explain that God’s plan for Abraham was to start the family of

     God.
b. To be faithful in keeping one’s word or promise.
c. To pray fervently an act of hope.

Life Situation
                                     God Provides

       There was a famine in a certain place near Barangay Kolon. The
people were suffering from hunger for almost a year. They did not get
anything in their farm. The people did not lose hope but instead, they

spent time for praying to their patron saint, performing religious practices
like praying the rosary while having a procession around their barrio.]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Values Development

Are we ready to do as God wishes even when it is hard to obey?

       Recall your everyday life experiences at home, in school, in the
community. It will help you personally relate the sacrifice that you often
made.

       How did you answer your mother when she called for you to help in
the kitchen?

       How did you feel when your teacher asked you to make something
which was hard for you to do?

       How did you perform your work in the church when the priest told
you to clean and pick up pieces of paper around?]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Proclamation of the Word of God

          God said to Abraham, “Leave your country, your family and
your father’s house, for the land I will show you. I will make you a great
nation; I will bless you and make your name so famous that it will be
used as a blessing. I will bless those who bless you. I will curse those
who slight you. All the tribes of the earth shall bless themselves by you.

          So Abraham went as God told him and Lot went with him.
Abraham was seventy – five years old when he left Haran. Abraham
took his wife, Sarah, his nephew Lot, all the possessions they had
amassed and the people they had acquired in Haran. They set off for
the land of Canaan, and arrived there.

Genesis 12: 1

                                                                    –5

What did God say to Abraham?

Who were the companions of Abraham?

What do you think was the purpose of God in sending Abraham to the
Land of Promise?]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Knowing our Faith

       The Bible tells us that Abraham had many descendants and
workmen with him. Abraham received the call from God to leave his
country, relatives and his father’s home and go to the land of promise, so
he will be blessed and make his name famous, as Father of all Nation.
Abraham kept thinking and thinking about it, until he finally decided to
follow the command of God. God’s command was this:

Leave your country Leave

                    your

Leave your friends  house

                    ?

       The question mark means God told them to leave, but they did not
know first where to go. Abraham trusted God even though he did not
understand. Abraham packed everything he had. He set out with his
wife, family, workmen, and animals for the land God would give to him
and his family and friends.

       Abraham was the first man called to help God with His plan to fulfill
His promise. He completely trusted God, left his country and arrived in
the Land of Promise.]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Challenges of our Faith

       Let us ask God to help us to be obedient always, and to be like
Abraham who answered: “Here I am, Lord, ready to do Your will, Teach
me to do it for You are my God.” Abraham showed his obedience and
trust in God when he said, “I am Your servant, Lord.” God’s plan was
for Abraham to start a new family, the family of God’s chosen People.
Abraham was kind to the strangers. Through the strangers God
promised Abraham and Sarah a child. They named the child Isaac.
Abraham understood more and more that God is faithful to His promises
and that He is a powerful and loving God.

       When Abraham received his Son, Isaac, he saw that God is very
powerful, loving and He kept His promises. Abraham wanted to answer
God’s call. He was ready to do anything God wanted him to do. He
offered his only son. God asked Abraham directly to do this. But, God
does not ask us directly. God asks us through others to make sacrifices.

       We should think of our powerful and loving God when we say the
Act of Hope. Let us always trust that God will keep His promises to take
us to heaven, if we keep His commandments.

Enhancing our Faith

Activity:

Dramatize the scene of the visit of God’s messengers to Abraham:

       One day, while Abraham was setting alone at the door, he saw
three men coming towards him. He ran to meet them, and insisted
them to stay with him.]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[He told Sarah, his wife to prepare food and drink for the guests.
While they were eating, one of the guests told Abraham that within a
year, Sarah would have a Son. Sarah, who was listening inside the door
of the tent, thought this was impossible. Abraham and Sarah were too
old to have children. It seems these visitors were sent by God, and that all
of it was part of God’s plan.

       About a year later, when Sarah became the mother of a son, she
understood that the travelers have told the truth. Abraham gave his son
a name, Isaac. Abraham’s son grew up strong and healthy. Having
been born after so many years of waiting, he was the joy and hope of his
parents. They loved him more than themselves.

       One day, God spoke to Abraham again. God asked Abraham to
do something very hard because He knew Abraham loved Him.
Abraham obeyed God. He set up an altar for the great sacrifice. He
laid Isaac on the altar and was ready to kill him when an angel from God
stopped him. Abraham then took a ram and sacrificed it to the Lord for
saving his son, Isaac.

Living our Faith

       The sacrifices God asks of us are not always as hard as the one He
asked Abraham to do.

How does God ask us to do little sacrifices?

a. through our parents at home

b. through our teachers in school

c. through our community leaders]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Illustrate your answers inside the boxes.
a.
b.]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[c.

Celebrating our Faith

God tested the faith and trust of Abraham by asking him to make a very
difficult sacrifice.

What about us? Let us answer God’s call today by being obedient and
do it cheerfully.

( Light one candle on the altar.)

Let us pray together:

In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit, Amen.]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[O God, we believe in You. We hope in You. We love You. We offer You
all what we think and do or say. We obey You. We love You.
Glory be to the Father and to the Son and to the Holy Spirit. As it was in

the beginning is now and ever shall be world without end, Amen.

Message from Marie Rivier

My dear children,

                            You must say and do nothing until you have prayed
                    and thought about the matter: until you have sought the
                    will of God.]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Lesson              Through the Scripture

  God               4
Speaks

Expected Outcomes:

a. To explain that God speaks to us in the Mass through the Liturgy of the

Word.

b. To respect others while reading the Word of God.

c. To participate actively in reciting the prayers and responses during

the Mass.

Life Situation

                    Listening Attentively

Nida and Jerne were getting ready for school. Their mother told

them to pray before leaving. They followed the instruction of their

mother.]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[When they reached the school their teacher told them to listen to
the announcement of the principal. Nida and Jerne listened
attentively while the other pupils were talking to one another.
When they entered the classroom their teacher asked them about the
announcement of the principal.

       Nida and Jerne were congratulated by their teacher because they
were the only ones who got the right answer. After the dismissal, they
went home and they told their mother what happened. Their mother was
happy because they did the right thing.

Values Development

What kind of children were Nida and Jerne?

How about their classmates?

If you are in the place of Nida and Jerne, what would you do?

What do you think would happen if you don’t listen to the
announcement?

Why is it important to listen to someone?

What happens when we listen attentively to God’s words during the
Mass?

Activity:

Group Sharing: Five or Six pupils in a group.

       Tell your classmates about what you heard from the readings and
the homily of the priest when you attended the Holy Mass.

       What did you learn from the homily of the priest? How did you
receive God’s message?]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[Proclamation of the Word of God

     One night Eli who was by then half blind, was lying down in his
room. The lamp of God was still lighted and Samuel was lying down in
the house of Yahweh where the Ark of God was located. Then Yahweh
called. “Samuel! Samuel!” Samuel answered, “I am here! And ran to Eli
saying,” I am here for you called me,” But Eli said, I did not call. Lie
down again.” Samuel went back. Then Yahweh called again, “Samuel!
Samuel” and Samuel stood up and went to Eli saying, “I am here for
you called me.“ But Eli said, “I did not call you, my son. Go back and lie
down,” now Samuel did not yet know Yahweh and the word of
Yahweh had not yet been revealed to him. But Yahweh called Samuel
for the third time. Samuel stood up and went to Eli saying, “I am here,
for you called me.” Then Eli realized that Yahweh was calling the boy
and he said to Samuel, “Go lie down, and if he calls you again, say,
“Speak, Yahweh, for your servant hears.” So Samuel went back and lay
down.

     Then Yahweh came and stood before Samuel, calling as he did
before. “Samuel! Samuel!” and Samuel answered. “Speak, for your
servant hears.” Then Yahweh said to Samuel, “Look, I am about to do
something in Israel which will scare everyone who hears about it. On
that day, I will punish Eli and fulfill all that I have spoken against his
family from beginning to end. You will tell him that I am about to punish
his family forever, because he was aware that his sons were
blaspheming God but he did not stop them. Therefore I swear that
the sin of Eli’s family shall never be atoned for by sacrifice or by any
offering.”]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[Samuel lay down until morning. Then he opened the doors of
Yahweh’s house. Samuel was afraid to tell the vision to Eli but Eli called
him and said, “Samuel, my son.” Samuel answered. “I am here.” Eli
asked, “What did Yahweh tell you? Do not hide from me. May God
punish you if you hide anything from me.” So Samuel told him
everything. Then Eli said, “It is Yahweh. Let him do what seems good to
him.”

                                              1Samuel 3: 1-18

Who was calling Samuel?

How did Samuel receive the message from God?

Knowing our Faith

God speaks to us through the Holy Scripture written in the Bible. He

also speaks to people around us, through His beautiful creatures,

through the church in the Eucharistic celebration and to all of us.

       When we are at Mass, we can hear God speaking to us through the
readings. On Sundays, the first reading is taken from the Holy Scripture in
the Old Testament and the second reading is taken from the New
Testament of the Bible. But on ordinary days readings are taken from the
New Testament like from one of the letters of St. Paul or from the Acts of
the Apostles. The responsorial psalm is taken from the different Psalms in
the Old Testament. The most important of these readings is the Gospels
according to Matthew, Mark, Luke or John. They are given greatest act
of respect because all the readings from the Holy Bible are the Word of
God.]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[CCC 109

       We believe that it is God who is speaking to us when the priest
explains the message from the Gospel reading during the homily. We
listen attentively because God is also speaking to us through the priest.

Challenges of our Faith

       We must participate in the proclamation of the Word of God.
Sometimes we are asked to read the first reading or second reading
during the Mass. We must prepare ourselves and read the Sacred
Scripture with love and respect.

       We share our time and talent in proclaiming the Word of God
because we are all children of God and members of the Church.
Others are talented in singing the responsorial psalms especially on
Sundays and on special occasions.

       By speaking, reading and listening to the word of God we show
how much we respond to God’s Word with love and respect of God.

       Let us remember that when we respond to an invitation to read the
Word of God at home, in school, in the community especially in the
Church we obey God and live the Christian way of life with Jesus Christ
as the center of our being.]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[Enhancing our Faith

A. What did you learn from the Word of God
       taken from the First Book of Samuel 3: 1-18?
       Art it out in your CL notebook.

B. In order to understand the Word of God through the “readings”
     especially during the Mass we must listen attentively. Where do we
     get the readings when we proclaim the Word of God?

       First Reading: ________________________
       Responsorial Psalm: ________________________
       Second Reading: ________________________
       Gospel Reading: ________________________

Living our Faith

       Every time we attend the Holy Mass we should be like Samuel
because he responded to the call of God attentively.

       We will also obey our parents, teachers, and elders or other people
who are in authority.

       Be ready to help at home when you are called to do for the glory
of God.

Celebrating our Faith

       Let us say together a short prayer thanking God for the blessings we
received today:

       Thank You, God for giving us the talent to proclaim the word of
God, for the gift of understanding to share to others and the grace of
living the Gospel message, Amen.]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[Let us sing together:

       Listen, Listen, listen everyone
       God is here for you and He is here for me.
       Listen, listen, listen can’t you hear.
       His love is here to stay,
       His love is ever new.

       Glory to the Father, sing glory to the Son.
       Glory to the Spirit, glory, glory everyone.
       Glory on the earth He made it, glory up above.
       Glory, glory everybody we have seen the Father’s love!

Message from Marie Rivier

                             My dear children,

                               Go, filled with zeal and trust. Go with fire! Be joyful
                        messengers of the Good News. Heaven calls you for the
salvation of souls. It is Jesus and Mary who journey with you in the spirit of
faith. I send you in their name.]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[Lesson Know Jesus Through the Bible

  5

   We

Expected Outcomes:
a. To tell that the Bible is the Holy Book.
b. To show love and respect in handling the Bible.
c. To pray to God and thank Him for giving us stories of Jesus in the Bible.

Life Situation

                                                Read and Share
Dave: Have you ever been in the hospital?
Gloria: Yes, I have visited sick people there.

Dave: Do you know someone there?
Gloria: Sure! Anne who was a nurse, and a cousin of Helen and Roy.]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[(Helen and Roy entered)

Dave: Helen, have you seen the photo of your   cousin, Anne was on
            the front page of the newspaper?

Roy: Yes the picture showed her with a young man who had been
            sick with polio.

Helen: The other nurses and doctors had been good friends to him.

Gloria: And Anne had helped to make him well.

Roy: It had taken a long time, and Anne had helped a lot.

Helen: The story was printed on the paper beside the photo so that
            thousands of people could read it.

       So, Helen and Roy took the cutting to school, and their teacher said
that it reminded her of a story we can read in the Bible, the story about a
man was cured by Jesus.

Value Development

What were Dave and Gloria talking about?

Who was with Anne on the front page of the newspaper?

Who helped the man to make him well?

What did Helen and Roy do with the picture of Anne who helped the
man?

What did their teacher say?]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[How
about
you? Do
you want
to hear
the story
of how
Jesus
helped
other
people?

Are you interested to know more about Jesus?

Look at the picture below and describe it.

 Proclamation of the Word of God

               In those days, the emperor issued a decree that a census of
 the whole empire should be taken. This first census was taken while
 Quirinius was governor of Syria. Everyone has to register in his own town.
 So, the people traveled and Joseph set out from Nazareth of Galilee.
 As he belonged to the family of David and was even a descendant of
 David, he went to Judea to David’s town of Bethlehem to be
 registered with Mary, his wife, who was with child. They were in
 Bethlehem when the time came for her to have her child and she gave
 birth to a son, her firstborn. She wrapped him in the manger, because
 there was no place for them in the living room.

                                                                                                                  Luke 2: 1–7]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[When Christ finally was born, He did not seem to be like anyone
great, or the Son of a king. Even though He was the Lord of all things, He
had no place to be born, no home of His own. He, who owned
everything, had nothing for Himself.

       When we feel that we need many things, do we think of Jesus in
Bethlehem? Do we think of other people especially the victims of
calamities like fire and flood that many people lost their houses and their
belongings? Do we feel disappointed if others have more than we have?

Knowing our Faith

       The Bible is the story of salvation. It is the Good News inspired by the
Holy Spirit and explained to us by the Church. It is a holy book which is
different from the other textbooks. It has God as its author and it helps us
to know and love Jesus Christ. A life of prayer is nourished by reading the
Bible. It is the primary source of the Church teaching about God.

       There are two main parts of the Bible:
       The first part is called the Old Testament. In it we learn about
creation. We also learn how God prepared men for the coming of His
Son, Jesus our Savior.

       The second part is called the New Testament. It tells about the life of
Jesus, his words and actions. He says and does many things to lead us to
his Father.

       We call this book the Holy Bible and the best book in the world
because it is the Word of God. It comes to us from God. The Holy Spirit
helped certain people to write it and the Holy Spirit helps us to
understand it.]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[Challenges of our Faith

The Bible tells us how our heavenly Father keeps His promise.
       We know that God our Father loves us so much and we believe in

Him that through the story in the gospel we learned that Mary was
chosen as the Mother of Jesus, our Savior. He comes to us in the Bible,
when we receive Him in Holy Communion, in all the people we meet and
also in all those whom we love. Jesus came to us humble and simple.
Can we encourage people at home, in school or in the community to
listen to the readings in the church every time we attend the Holy Mass?
We ought to learn many stories about God in the Bible. We show to
others the way we live the example of Jesus.

       We are encourage at home or in the Parish church to have a place
for a Bible so that everyone is welcomed to read and learn the stories
about God the Father, Son and Holy Spirit.

       We show love and respect for the written Word of God in the
Lectionary or in the Missal. As we listen to the Word of God on Sundays,
let us think about the message that God is giving us.]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[Enhancing our Faith

Let us study and explain the illustration about knowing what is in the

Bible.

The Holy Bible

Brings God’s Tells us of God’s

Message to      Love

        us

        Was written by many men who were guided by the Holy Spirit

                     Draw an open holy book]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[Living our Faith

       Write your own prayer thanking God for His message of love in the
Holy Bible.
Loving Father,
_______________________________________________________________________
_______________________________________________________________________
_______________________________________________________________________
_______________________________________________________________________
_______________________________________________

Celebrating our Faith

Everyone is encouraged to bring a Bible.

Say a short prayer in your own words. Then we will all sing: “Good News”

Yes, Lord I will go to tell the “Good News”.

Message from Marie Rivier

My dear children,

       Be faithful to grace and all will follow. I hope to have in you an
imitator of the Holy Child Jesus, like Him, obedient in all things to His
Father’s will. If you need anything, ask me for it. I beg of you. Please
imitate the virtues of the child Jesus, meek and humble of heart.]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[UNIT 2

WE PROFESS OUR FAITH

                                       Let Us get Together]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[WE PROFESS OUR FAITH

       This unit focuses on the Doctrinal Truths of our faith which include
the Blessed Trinity, the Human Person, the Church and the Blessed Virgin
Mary. The learners are introduced to learn about the basic doctrines of
the Apostles’Creed. They are gradually led to belief, conviction and
commitment of their faith. They are also invited and challenged to take
an active role in the mission of the church as baptized members. The
learners are presnted a model of faith and virtues in the person of the
Blessed Virgin Mary.

                              The Author

Marie Rivier, Woman of Faith]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[Lesson  6

              We Believe in God the Father

Expected Outcomes:
a. To realize that when we pray the Creed we express our faith to

     believe in one God.
b. To speak to God sincerely and lovingly.
c. To ask God for His blessings and thank Him in prayer.

Life Situation

Paste the picture of each community helper.
Look at each picture. Do you know what these people
can do for you? Describe each. Tell how each one helps you.

                                                            Picture
                                                         of a doctor

                                                            Picture
                                                        of a mother

                                                    A.
                                                    B.]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[Picture        Picture
of a priest  of a teacher

  Picture        Picture
     of a     of a farmer

policeman          D.
                   F.
    C.
     E.]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[Picture  Picture

of a driver of a nun

                          G.
                          I.

                        Picture
                      of a nurse

                          H.]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[Value Development

What do you believe in each of these people?
How do you show that you believe in them?
Why do you depend on them?
What happens if they do not help us?

       Who else do you believe in more than the people around which
you have to love, trust and believe above all things?

 Proclamation of the Word of God

       On the evening of that first day of the week, even though the
 disciples had locked the doors of the place where they were for fear of
 the Jews, Jesus came and stood before them. “Peace be with you,”
 He said. When He had said this, He showed them His hands and His
 side. At the sight of the Lord the disciples rejoiced. “Peace be with
 you,” He said again, ”As the Father has sent, so I send you.” Then, He
 breathed on them and said: “Receive the Holy Spirit. If you forgive
 men’s sins, they are forgiven them; if you hold them bound, they are
 held bound.” It happened that one of the twelve, Thomas (means
 “Twins”) was absent when he came. The other disciples kept telling
 him: “we have seen the Lord!” His answer was, “I’ll never believe it
 without probing the nail-prints in his hands, without putting my finger in
 the nail marks and my hand into his side.”

                                                                                                             John 20: 19-25]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[A week later the disciples were once more in the room, and this
 time Thomas was with them. Despite the locked doors, Jesus came and
 stood before them. “Peace be with you,” he said then to Thomas:
 “Take your finger and examine my hands, put your hand into my side.
 Do not persist in your unbelief, but believe!” Thomas said in response
 “my Lord and my God!” Jesus then said to him: You became a believer
 because you saw me. Blest are they who have not seen and have
 believed,” Jesus performed many other signs as well – signs not
 recorded here – in the presence of his disciples. But these have been
 recorded to help you believe that Jesus is the Messiah, the Son of God,
 so that through this faith you may have life in his name.

                                                                                                           John 20: 26 - 31

       Thomas did not believe first because he was away when Jesus
came to visit the disciples after his resurrection. When Jesus came back,
Thomas saw Jesus and he believed Him and said, “My Lord and my
God.” Jesus said, “Happy are those who do not see me but who believe
in me.”

       What message did you learn from the gospel according to John
which you could proclaim to others?

Knowing our Faith]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[Apostles’ Creed.
 1. I believe in God, the Father Almighty, creator of heaven and earth.
  2. And in Jesus Christ, His only Son, our Lord,
  3. Who was conceived by the Holy Spirit and born of the Virgin Mary.
  4. Suffered under Pontius Pilate, was crucified, died and was buried.
  5. He descended into hell; on the third day, he rose again from the

      dead;
  6. He ascended into heaven, and is seated at the right hand of the

      Father Almighty;
  7. From there he will come to judge the living and the dead.
  8. I believe in the Holy Spirit.
  9. The Holy Catholic Church, the communion of saints
10. the forgiveness of sins,
11. the resurrection of the body,
12. and life everlasting, Amen.

                                                                                                                       CCC 178]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[CCC 189

Challenges of our Faith

       When we attend Mass, we are encouraged to join
with the priest and the people to recite the prayer, the Creed to profess
our Faith that we believe in God, the Father, Creator of heaven and
earth, we believe in Jesus Christ, our Savior and in God the Holy Spirit, the
one who guides, helps us and sanctifies us.

       During our baptism we profess our faith but it was our parents and
godparents who made our promises for us.

       Every Easter Sunday we recite our baptismal promises or renewal of
baptism with the people during the Eucharistic Celebration.
When we go to confess our sins to the priest, we depend on Jesus Christ,
his power to forgive us.

       We believe that Jesus Christ comes to us when we receive him in
the Holy Communion. We accepted to receive the wholeness of Body of
Christ when we say Amen before the priest who gives us Jesus in the form
of the consecrated bread.

       That is why we show our love and respect, when we recite the
prayers not only during the Mass but also when we pray at home, in
school or with the other people in the community.
We have to be sincere in reciting the prayer, the
Creed, to show how much we love God.]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[Enhancing our Faith                                      heaven and
                                                         Son,
1. Recite the Prayer: “The Apostles Creed”               conceived by

2. Try to recall and recite your baptismal promises.     and

3. Fill in the blanks:
     I believe in God,
     Creator of
     And in Jesus Christ, His only

     Who was
     the

     Born of the

     Suffered under
     Was crucified, died

He                                                       descended
                                                         third day
On the                                                .

He ascended into

And is seated at the

From there he will come to

I believe in the

The Holy

The communion of

The forgiveness of

The resurrection of

And life

AMEN.

Living our Faith

After the homily of the priest at Mass,

we profess our faith when we say the Apostles’ Creed.

We tell God that we believe in Him.]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[We believe that He is the creator of all things.
We believe in Jesus Christ who came to save us
from our sins. He is our Savior.
We believe in the Holy Spirit, who lives in us and in His Church. He is our
sanctifier.

Show in your drawing that you are the family of believers.

Celebrating our Faith

1. Let us pray the Holy Rosary and say first the Apostles Creed praising
     the Lord for sharing with us, His great love.

2. Closing Prayer: Let us pray together this prayer:
     “Loving father, we believe in You. We praise You. We love You. We
     thank You for everything You had done to us. Teach us, to remember
     that every time we say the Apostles’ Creed we should pray it with
     respect and it must come from our hearts and so we glorify You,
     Amen.”

Message from Marie Rivier

My dear children,

       Have courage and put your trust in God. Love and believe in Him.
Your hearts would burn with love whenever you speak about God.]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[Lesson              About His Father

 Jesus                               7
Tells Us

Expected Outcomes:

a. To explain that Jesus teaches us about His Father’s love.

b. To show gratefulness to God for providing us our needs.

c. To thank God for giving us what we need.

Life Situation

Read the short story of a Rancher and find out what he needs.

                    A Good Rancher

There was a man named Fernando, a very good rancher. He had

good strong horses and cattle. The house he lived in was just right for him.

He enjoyed his life being a cowboy.]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[Every day is just perfect. He rides out with the cowboys and rounds
up for the cattle, and brings them back for food and water. The ranch
always provides plenty of food and water for the cattle. He does the
work by himself everyday. He couldn’t ask for anything more.

       One day his parents came to visit his ranch. They brought him a
present, a big cookbook that had 2,000 recipes in it. He didn’t have
much time for cooking so what should he do?

Value Development

The rancher doesn’t need the cookbook.

He is always happy with his ranch and cattle.

What is the rancher doing?

What does he have in his house?

Why do you think the rancher doesn’t need the cookbook?

What is important in the life of the rancher?

What do you think the rancher need more than his food?

Why is food necessary? Is there anything much important than food?

What happened if we do not have shelter and clothing?

What did Jesus say about life? What must we do to God in order to live?]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[Proclamation of the Word of God

       Jesus said to his disciples, I tell you not to worry about your life.
 What are we to eat, or your body? What are we to put on? For your life
 is more than food and the body more than clothing. Look at the crows:
 they neither sow nor reap; they have no storehouses and no barns; yet
 God feed them. How much more important are you than the birds!
 Which of you for all his worrying can make himself a bit taller? And if
 you are not able to control such a little thing, why do you worry about
 the rest? Look at the wild flowers they do not spin or weave; yet I tell
 you, even Solomon with all his wealth was mot clothed as one of these.
 But if in the fields God so clothes the grass which is alive today and
 tomorrow is thrown into the oven, how much more will he clothe you,
 people of little faith.

       As for you do not set your heart on what you are to eat and drink;
 stop worrying. Let all the nations of the world run after this thing. Seek
 rather the Kingdom and these things will be given to you as well.

                                                                                                           Luke 12: 22 - 31

       Jesus is telling us that God will provide us our needs as long as we
put our faith and trust in Him. God will give us all that is necessary to live.
Life itself is the most important among the many things we use or want.

What did Jesus say to His disciples?

What did He say about life?]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[Knowing our Faith

       God our Father, is our creator and He provides us all important
things that we need.

       He loves us very much. He wants to give us many blessings to show
His love. He gives us only what is necessary for our lives.

       Jesus told us “Do not be concerned too much for your needs, what
you are to eat, or for your body, what you are to wear. Life is more
important than food and the body is more important than clothing.”

       We learned from Jesus that God His Father made man and He
gave man trees, plants and animals necessary for our lives. God shares
His power with us so we are responsible for the world. We do what is
good to add beauty to the world. We praise God for the wonders of His
creations.

       We tell God that we love Him. We thank Him for all He has given us.
He will always take care of us and give us everything we need to live as
His children. Sometimes He does not give us what we ask, because He
knows what is really necessary for our good.

       God loves us so much that He sent His own Son Jesus, to be born on
earth to show us the way to Him. Jesus worked and prayed for us.

       He gave Himself to His Father for our sakes, dying on the cross for us.
He has shown us how to live. He leads us to the Heavenly Father.

                                                                                                    Catechism Book p. 5

                                                                                             CCC 240]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[We believe that everything comes from the Father. He provides us
what we need at home, in school and other important things we need in
life.

       For instance, the important things needed for living are food, shelter
and clothing. Why is food necessary? People who are victims of fire and
floods, need food in order to survive. Shelter is necessary to protect our
bodies from the weather. How does God give it to us? Our parents get
food from the supermarket. Building houses are made by the carpenters.

       God wants us to put our faith and trust in Him. God will give us all we
need to live.

       We do not need to worry. God gives us what we need. He gives us
our parents, friends, and teachers. We should thank God by loving others
just like Jesus.

       We should be happy when we share to others like helping the poor
and the needy.

Enhancing our Faith

Share your thoughts:

Why is God our Father?

Whom did God send to us?

What does Jesus teach us about his Father?

Write the necessary things we need in life:
_______________________________________________________________________
_______________________________________________________________________
_______________________________________________________________________
___________________________________________________]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[What can you do to thank God for giving us Jesus who teaches us
to love?

Living our Faith

       God gives us also the power to think, help and work.

       Let us help one another at home or in school or with our neighbors
to take care of the things around us. We should not waste food but give
to the poor.

       We help to make our surroundings clean by putting the garbage in
the right place.

       We help the victims of different calamities by giving even the
smallest amount we can offer and by praying for them in the spirit of love
and concern.]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[Celebrating our Faith

       When we pray to God, our Father, we show Him that we believe in
Him, hope in Him and love Him. We tell Him what we need every day. We
thank Jesus for teaching us all about His Father.

       Let us form a circle and hold hands with one another as we pray
together the “Our Father.”

       Let us sing together, “Give Thanks”.

       Give thanks with a grateful hearts.

       Give thanks to the Holy One.

       Give thanks because He’s given Jesus Christ, His Son.2x

(Chorus:)
And now let the weak say, ”I am strong.”
Let the poor say, “ I am rich.”
Because of what the Lord has done for us.
Give thanks. ( repeat )
Give thanks. 3x

Message from Marie Rivier

My dear children,

                           Do not neglect the poor, I beg you! At this hour, it is
                    our duty to care for the poor of Jesus Christ. We must do to
                    them what we would have done for Jesus. Give your
                    compassionate love for the poor.]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[Lesson  Holy Spirit Lives In Us

   The        8

Expected Outcomes:
a. To tell the role of the Holy Spirit in our lives.
b. To believe in the Holy Spirit as the true God.
c. To thank God for sending a helper, the Holy Spirit.

Life Situation

                                           The Twin Sisters
       Mercy and Merthy are twin sisters. Their parents send them to a
Catholic school.

       One day, they had a misunderstanding. Their parents reminded
them to love each other so they must grow as happy children. Both of
them listened to the advice of their parents.

       Finally, they             reconciled
with each other                  and lived in
love wherever they               go.]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[Values Development

Who are the twin sisters in the story?
What did their parents remind them to do?
What is the role of the parents in the life of the twin sisters?
Who else could guide us aside from our parents?
Do you know that there is someone who lives in us and help us in our
daily life?

 Proclamation of the Word of God

       Jesus said to his disciples,
       “I have much more to tell you, but you cannot bear it now. When
 he comes, however, being the Spirit of Truth, he will guide you to all the
 truth.]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[He will not speak on his own, but will speak only what he hears, and
will announce to you the things to come. I am doing this so that he will
give glory to me, because he will have received from me what he will
announce to you. All that the Father Has belongs to me. That is why I
said that he will take from what is mine and declare it to you.

                                       John 16: 12 - 15

What did Jesus promise His disciples?
What does the Holy Spirit do to us?

       Whoever is a Christian knows that he lives in the presence of God.
Wherever he goes, he is in the holy presence of the Father, Son and Holy
Spirit. The Spirit of Truth is with us, Christians. The Spirit teaches us what he
knows from the Father, and the Son, brings this blessing to all of us until
the end of time.]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[Knowing our Faith

The Holy Spirit is God, the third person in the Blessed Trinity.
       The Holy Spirit lives in us because we are baptized people. It is the

gift of Jesus to us.
       The Holy Spirit lives in us, giving light to our minds, love to our hearts

and life to our souls.
The Holy Spirit is a guide and an inspiration in doing good.

                                                                                        CCC 687

Challenges of our Faith

       We all know that God loves us as faithful children
and we love Him, too. Every day God is loving us and watching over us.
He makes us happy. Even if we have troubles, disappointments, deep
down inside we are happy people. No one can take us away from God.
God will always take care of us. Because the Holy Spirit lives within us, we
are happy. We always ask the Holy Spirit to stay with us, guide us and
help us to choose what is right and good.]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[Enhancing our Faith

Just a simple recall what you can remember:

Recite this prayer by heart:

Come Holy Spirit, fill the hearts of your faithful,
And enkindle in them the fire of your love.
Send forth Your Spirit and they shall be created,
And you shall renew the face of the earth.

       O God, who did instruct the heart of the faithful by the light of the
Holy Spirit, grant us in the same Spirit to be truly wise and ever rejoice in
His consolation, through the same Christ, our Lord, Amen.

       Compose your own prayer to the Holy Spirit. Write in hour notebook.

Living our Faith

       We invite one another at home to invoke the name of the Holy Spirit
to enlighten our mind and be in the presence of God before we will start
the prayer and before reading the Word of God from the Bible.

       We ask the Holy Spirit to stay with us when we study our lesson to
help us and guide us during our examination days. It teaches us how to
be honest in class activities and strengthen us to be happy in our life.

       We can do good actions because of the Holy Spirit like when we
study, pray, listen and play.]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[Celebrating our Faith

       In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit,
Amen.

Let us sing together:

       Come to us, Spirit of Jesus
       Fill the hearts of your faithful ones
       Send your comfort down from above
       Touch our lives with a fire of love
       Come to Us, Spirit of God.

Let us recite together the Glory Be.

Message from Marie Rivier

                        My dear children,

                            Depend only on Jesus Christ, act according to his spirit
                    and do all his love.]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[Lesson n Community of Believers

     The            9
   Christia

Expected Outcomes:

a. To define the Church as Christian Community of believers.

b. To show respect to one another while building the community.

c. To pray to God everyday for peace in the community.

Life Situation

Describe each picture below. Tell what the children are doing.

Write the name of 5 persons in each box below whom you want to:

                    Be always with

14
..

25
..

3 Pl

.a

4y
.w
   it
5  h

.

W1
o.
r
k2
w.

it 3

h.

      4
1.
.

      5
2.
.

3
.]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[VDp
aem
l ve
uen
el t
so

Why do you want to be always with them?
What do you do when you work together?
Why do you select the persons whom you want to play with?
How about those who are not in your lists?
How do you feel if you don’t belong to any group in the Church
organization?

       We are all members of Christian community. Each one of us
belongs to a certain GKK, to a family, to a school and a barangay. Let us
try to find out what do we usually do if we belong to a community of
believers.]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[Proclamation of the Word of God

            The first community was faithful to the teaching of the Apostles,
 the common life of sharing, the breaking of bread and the prayers.

                A holy fear came upon all the people for many wonders and
 miraculous signs were done by the Apostles. Now all believers lived
 together and shared all their belongings. They would sell their property
 and all they had and distribute the proceeds to others according to
 their need. Each day they met together in the Temple area; they
 broke bread in their homes they shared their food with great joy and
 simplicity of heart; they praised God and won the people favors. And
 everyday the Lord added to their number those who were being saved.

                                                                                                               Act 2: 42 – 47

       Describe the first community who was faithful in the teaching of the
Apostles.

What happened to their belongings?

What did the believers do in the temple area?

Knowing our Faith

Church is the community of believers.

We believe that we belong to the Holy Catholic Church.]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[The true Church is one, holy, catholic and apostolic, founded by
Jesus Christ. The members must be united. It must teach us in faith and
provide the members to lead a holy life. It must be for all peoples of
every nation and must teach the same faith everywhere. That’s why
Christ commanded us to go and make Him known and loved
everywhere. The Apostles were the first one to spread the teachings of
the Church and proclaim the Gospel to everyone.

                                                                                                       (My Catholic Faith)

                                                                                       CCC 763

       The Church could be a community of families. The
family is the Church in the home. Jesus began his
earthly mission within a family, where faith life begins and grows to
maturity. It is where Christian conscience is formed, and Christian prayer
and worship nurtured. The family is a true foundation for Basic Ecclesial
Communities, a model of relationships in the Church; that all should form
one family and obey the will of the Father through the Holy Spirit (PCP II
419 – 22)

Challenges of our Faith

       God wants us to belong to His Family. All baptized persons belong
to God’s family.]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[Jesus is telling us “Go and preach the Good News to everyone.”
Make Jesus Christ known and loved everywhere. Jesus wanted us to be
his followers. He sent us the Holy Spirit to do His work even when we are
at home, in school, in the church or in the community where we are.

       If we are living in a small community, usually the families gather
together in their GKK chapel and shared together the Word of God in
the liturgical celebration as well as in the sharing of love in the Eucharist.
The members of the families work together in giving concern to one
another and help each other grow in the sense of responsibility for one
another.

       As children of God, we should continue to show good examples
and lead others to God. The Holy Spirit will inspire us in doing our work,
giving us the Spirit of wisdom, understanding, counsel, fortitude,
knowledge, piety and fear of God.

       We will be inspired to participate actively in the different
organization of our GKK. Perhaps we can join in the group of lectors,
collectors, choir, altar servers, children of Mary and church beautification
committees.

       We try to participate in the community of believers by sharing our
food and clothes to help the poor and victims of natural calamities.

       We join with other groups with one heart and one mind and give joy
to everyone.]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[Enhancing our Faith

       Write a word on each brick that shows how we can build a strong
community. Choose from the words on the page.

Care
Join
Thank
Grab
Quarrel
Anger
Forgive
Help
Envy
Peace
Respect

Living our Faith

- Invite your parents to attend the prayer session in your GKK.

- Volunteer to lead the prayer especially as leader in the liturgy
     celebration, like praying the rosary.

- Organize a group to maintain the cleanliness of your chapel.

- Help distribute food to the needy and victims of calamities.]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[Celebrating our Faith

Let us pray together:

       Heavenly Father, help us to be faithful in gathering together. Thank
You for inviting us to become members of Your Church. Make us aware
that we have important part to do in the community where we belong.
Help us to be active members in doing our own responsibilities. Amen.

Let us sing this song: In God’s Family

We are happy Christians so united in the Lord,

We belong to one family.

Jesus Christ has chosen us to carry on his life over every land and sea.

From the north and from the south and from the east and west,

He has called us all together!

And we are delighted that we are united into God’s own family.

And we are delighted that we are united into God’s own family.

Message from Marie Rivier

My dear children,

       Be for the world, an open Gospel so that everybody may reach
                        Jesus Christ in building community.]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[Lesson              of Christ

Mary,               10
Mother

Expected Outcomes:

a. To tell that Mary is the Mother of Jesus Christ.

b. To follow the virtues of Virgin Mary.

c. To say prayers and sing songs to Mary.

Life Situation

Mothers are special in the families. We learn many things from our

earthly mothers. We give them importance on Mothers’ Day. We respect

them and they become our model. We cherish what they teach us and

look at their examples being good to us and to others. They say kind

words when they talk to us and to our neighbors. We treasure their love

and care.

       Let us listen to our classmates as they tell us about their own mother.

A. Maria Elena
       “My mother is a teacher. She goes to school every day and

     teaches Grade Three pupils in section Champaga in our school. She
     loves all of us at home. We never missed our school days with her. We
     always arrived in school early and were ready to participate in her
     class. She became my class adviser. On some other days she brings
     us out for shopping to buy the necessary things we need. We are
     grateful to have an understanding and beautiful mother.”]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[B. Maria Anna
       “My mother is a vendor. She cooks peanuts and popcorn every

     morning and sell them in the market everyday. She earns money to
     pay for our transportation and also for our school accounts. She gives
     us also money to buy the food we need especially for our health
     break. She teaches us how to use money wisely. We are lucky to
     have a good and caring mother.”

C. Maria Mercedes
       “My mother is a housekeeper. She cooks food for us everyday. She

     takes good care of us every time we asked help from her. She sends
     us to a Catholic school, Presentation of Mary School of Clarin. She
     also teaches us how to work at home like cleaning our surroundings
     and making vegetable and flower gardens. In the evening she
     gathers us and teaches us how to pray especially the Holy Rosary
     together with all the members of our family. She brings us to attend
     the Holy Mass in our Parish church on Sundays and other Holy Days of
     obligation.

Values Development

What can you say about the role of a mother at home?
How does a mother care for her children?
Why do you need your mother to teach you?
What happens if your mother doesn’t know how to take good care of
you?]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[Mothers are special and important in every family.
Do you want to know more about someone who is the model of all
mothers?]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[Proclamation of the Word of God

         Angel Gabriel was sent by God to a town in Galilee called Nazareth
to a Virgin betrothed to a man named Joseph. The name of the Virgin was
Mary. The Angel said to her, Rejoice, so highly favored daughter. “The Lord is
with you!” Mary was deeply disturbed but the Angel said to her, “Mary do
not be afraid, You are to conceive and bear a Son, and you must name him
Jesus. Mary said to the Angel, “But how can this be since I am a Virgin?” the
Holy Spirit will come upon you, the Angel answered and the power of the
Most High will cover you with its shadow. Mary said, “I am the handmaid of
the Lord, let what you have said be done to me,” and the Angel left her.

                                                                                                          Luke 1: 26 – 38

        Near the cross of Jesus stood his mother, and his mother’s sister,
Mary the wife of Cleopas and Mary of Magdala. Seeing his mother and
the disciple he loved standing near her, Jesus said to his mother,
“Woman, this is your Son, then he told his disciple and he said, “This is
your mother.” And from that moment the disciple made a place for her
in his home.

                                                                                                        John 19: 25 – 27]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[Who was sent by God to go to Galilee?
What did Angel Gabriel say to Virgin Mary?
What was the answer of Virgin Mary?
Who is Virgin Mary?
What did Jesus say to His disciple, John?
What happened to Mary?

Knowing our Faith

       We are all entrusted to Mary. She is the Mother of Jesus Christ and
our Mother, too. She continues to love all of us. We pay homage to her
as an act of loving her. Every Christian must honor Mary who was the
humble handmaid of the Lord.

       We honor Mary by celebrating her many feast days during the
Church year.

       God, our Father, has already favored her as the Mother of Christ,
our Savior. The Church honors Mary and has declared her both Mother
and Virgin by the singular act of God. On Christmas, we honored the
Son; but on the first day of January, we celebrate her Motherhood, the
Solemnity of Mary.

       Another feast day of Mary is on November 21. We commemorate
on this day her offering of herself totally to God at the age of three years
old. She was presented by her parents, Joachim and Anne to the temple
and was accepted by God. We always remember her on the day when
she presented herself in the temple and she was given the title, Our Lady
of the Presentation.

       Every December 8 we also honor Mary on the Feast of the
Immaculate Conception. We remember her on this day as she has a part
of Gods’ plan of salvation from the beginning of her life. She was blessed
to be the Mother of Jesus. She received a special blessing from God
being born free from the original sin.]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[On August 15 we celebrate the Assumption of Mary into heaven as
a defined Doctrine of the Church which was a fairly recent reality. It is
important to realize that Mary received a special role in being the
Mother of the Son of God.

       September 8 is the Feast of the Nativity of the Blessed Virgin Mary.
We celebrate on this day the birthday of Mary. A birthday is always a
time when we should remember that we receive life from God. Let us
thank God on this day for the gift of Mary to all mankind.
We live with Mary as our model. She is the Mother of all Catholic
throughout the world. We know that she is the Mother of the Church and
our Mother, too. She received special role from God as the Mother of
Gods’ Son, Jesus.

Challenges of our Faith

       Like Mary, we are challenged to love and obey our parents. We
should also love the people of God, be generous and ready to offer our
helping hands to others especially to the poor and the needy.
Sometimes it is not easy to support others, not easy to obey our parents
and elders but we treasure the goodness of Mary because we believe
that she showed much love to God and truly gives us courage to follow
her examples.

Enhancing our Faith

A. Write down the dates of the following feasts of Mary:

       1. Motherhood of Mary

       2. Immaculate Conception

       3. Presentation of Mary

       4. Nativity of Mary]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[5.  Assumption of
Mary       Our Lady of the

       6.

Rosary

B. Why do we pray to Mary?

Living our Faith

We love Mary because she is the Mother of

Jesus. We also love her as our own Mother.

If we love Jesus, we should also love Mary and follow her example of
obedience and love for God.

We make a special devotion to her as a sign of our trust in her as the
Mother of Jesus and our Mother. We pray to her every day.

Celebrating our Faith

1. Let us sing this song:
               Immaculate Mother, we come at thy call
               And love at your altar before you we fall.

       Ave, Ave, Ave Maria 2x
               We pray for our mother, the Church upon earth
               And bless the sweetest lady,the land of our birth.

       Ave, Ave, Ave Maria.2x
       In grief and temptation, in joy and in pain
       We’ll seek you, our Mother, nor seek you in vain.
       Ave, Ave, Ave, Maria.2x]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[2. Let us pray together:
     Virgin Mary,
     We love you. We want to be like you, obedient, and humble, and
     with a complete faith and trust in God. We ask this through Jesus, your
     Son, our Lord. Amen.

3. Let us say 3 Hail Mary and Glory Be.

Message from Marie Rivier

                        My dear children,

                            Mary offers the same sacrifices as do poor and simple
                    children of God. She spent a good part of each day
                    pouring her heart to God in endless, joyous praise.]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[Lesson Honor Mary

 We 11

Expected Outcomes:
a. To tell that Mary is the most holy and exalted of all creatures.
b. To express one’s love and devotion to Blessed Virgin Mary.
c. To participate actively in praying the prayers to Mary.

Life Situation
                           A Short Story of Marie Rivier

       In the little town of Montpezat, Jean-Baptiste and Anne-Marie run
an inn and a small shop. On December 19, 1768, they were overjoyed by
the arrival in their household of third child, Marie. In the family, they
called her Marinette; she was baptized two days later.]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[Alas, when she was 16 months old, Marinette broke her hip! She
could no longer walk, even with the little crutches that were made for
her. Her mother, whose faith was strong, puts all her trust in the Blessed
Virgin. Every day, carrying her daughter, she went to the nearby chapel
of the Penitents and prayed in front of the statue of Our Lady of Pity.
Soon the little girl was sure that the Blessed Virgin will cure her. She
wanted to go to see her every day and for four years she implored, cried,
sucked, pleaded and even went as far as offering her a beautiful dress
and a hat!

       Then one day she had an idea, she went back and said, “Blessed
Virgin, cure me and I will bring little ones to you. I will teach them and I
will tell them to love you.” She did not forget her promise. Even when she
became crippled, Marie had lots of fun: she was carried at the back of
their house where she brought a joyful but quite noisy group of children.
She knew how to make herself obeyed and loved dearly. She invented
all sorts of games, telling stories and talking about our Father in heaven
who loved us. She was the “little mother” to the little children. When she
was six years old, her father died.

       The next day was the feast day of the Nativity of the Virgin Mary.
She asked for her crutches, long since abandoned and ….. A Miracle!
She started to walk again. In thanksgiving, she went along to offer her
pretty blue dress and her hat to the statue of Our Lady, as she had
promised.

Values Development

What happened to Marie?
Where did her mother bring her?
What did she say to the Blessed Virgin?
What was her promise to the Virgin Mary?
What happened after her father died?
How did Marie increase her love to Virgin Mary?
How about you? How do you honor Virgin Mary?]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[Proclamation of the Word of God

       When Jesus was nailed on the cross his mother, his mother’s sister
 Mary, who was the wife of Cleopas, and Mary of Magdala stood near
 the cross. Jesus saw his mother and the disciple, then he said to the
 mother. “Woman, this your son.” Then he said also to the disciple John,
 “There is your mother.” And from that moment the disciple took her to
 his own home.

                                                                                                          John 19: 25 – 27

       On the cross, Jesus gave up the last most beautiful and precious
possession that He had in this world, His own mother.

       Mary is Christ’s gift to us. We have received her as a blessing from
God. So, we have to express our love for her and be faithful in our
devotions to her. She is our mother and the Mother of the Church.
Therefore all Catholic around the world must honor her by praying to her
everyday.]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[Knowing our Faith

       Mary is the most holy and honored of all creatures who possessed
all the graces and gifts of God.

       Mary has been privileged among women, being the Mother of the
Son of God.

       Knowing what power a mother, and especially the Mother of God
has over her Son, we beg Mary to pray for us.
The principal prayers to the Blessed Virgin Mary:
Hail Mary, full of grace, the Lord is with you; blessed are you among
women and blessed is the fruit of your womb, Jesus. Holy Mary Mother of
God, pray for us sinners, now and at the hour of our death. Amen.

Hail Holy Queen, Mother of mercy, hail our life, our sweetness and our
                                     hope, to you do we cry poor banished children
                                     of Eve; to you do we send up our sighs,
                                     mourning and weeping in this valley of tears.
                                     Turn then most gracious advocate, your eyes of
                                     mercy towards us; and after this our exile, show
                                     to us the blessed fruit of your womb, Jesus. O
                                     Clement, O Loving, O Sweet Virgin Mary!
                                     Pray for us O Holy Mother of God.
                                     That we may be made worthy from the
                                     promises of Christ.

           The Memorare – Remember, O most gracious
           Virgin Mary, that never was it known, that
           anyone who fled to your protection, implored
           your help, or sought your intercession was left
           unaided. Inspired with this confidence, I fly unto
           you, O Virgins of Virgins, my mother to you I
           come; before you I stand sinful and sorrowful; O
           mother of the Word Incarnate despise not my
           petitions but in your mercy hear and answer

me. Amen.]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[The Angelus –
     V. The Angel of the Lord declared unto Mary.
     R. And she conceived by the power of the Holy Spirit,
       Hail Mary……………..
     V. Behold the handmaid of the Lord.
     R. Be it done unto me according to your word.
               Hail Mary…………….
     V. And the Word was made Flesh
     R. And dwelt among us Hail Mary…………..
     V. Pray for us, O Holy Mother of God
                                        R. That we may be made worthy of the
                                        promises of Christ.
                                        Let us pray:
                                        Pour forth, we beseech you, O Lord, Your
                                        grace into our hearts, that we to whom the
                                        Incarnation of Christ Your Son was made
                                        known by the message of an angel, may by
                                        His passion and cross be brought to the glory

of his Resurrection, through the same Christ our Lord. Amen.
Glory be………..

Under Mary’s protection – We fly to your patronage O Holy Mother of
God. Despise not our petitions in our necessities, but deliver us always
from all dangers O glorious and blessed Virgin.]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[The Rosary: It is a prayer in honor of Mary consisting of two hundred Hail
                   Mary and twenty Our Father accompanied by meditation
                   on the life of Jesus and Mary.

The Mysteries of Light (every Thursday)
The Baptism of Jesus

       The Wedding Feast at Cana
The Proclamation of the Kingdom, with the call to conversion.
The Transfiguration
The Institution of the Eucharist

The Joyful Mysteries (every Sunday and Saturday)

       The Annunciation
       The Visitation
       The Nativity
       The Presentation of Jesus in the Temple
       The Finding of Jesus in the Temple

 The Sorrowful Mysteries (every Tuesday and Friday)

       The Agony in the Garden
       The Scourging at the Pillar
       The Crowning with Thorns
       The Carrying of the Cross
       The Crucifixion

The Glorious Mysteries (every Wednesday and Sunday)
       The Resurrection
       The Ascension
       The Descent of the Holy Spirit
       The Assumption
       The Coronation of Mary as Queen of Heaven and Earth]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[Draw your Rosary Beads inside this box and label its part.]]></page><page Index="93"><![CDATA[Challenges of our Faith

       We received love and care from our very own Mother. Blessed
Virgin Mary was given the role as the Mother of the Church. Like our
Mother Mary shows her love and care for us. She always prays for our
protection. She wants us also to pray the Rosary which is a powerful
prayer to obtain grace of God through her intercession.

       Everyday we pray the Rosary devotedly, attentively and slowly. In
times of danger and calamity, the Rosary has been the means by which
miraculous aid has been obtained.]]></page><page Index="94"><![CDATA[Every Catholic should not fail to say at least five decades of the
Rosary each day. We are encouraged to pray the Rosary at home
together with our family. In school, we pay homage to Mary on the
occasion of her feast days offering flowers and praying the Rosary
especially on the month of October when we pray it daily. While
reciting the rosary, each one must hold his own rosary beads in his hand.

Enhancing our Faith

       Memorize the basic prayers such as Our Father, Hail Mary, Glory Be,
Hail Holy Queen, O My Jesus and the Apostle’s Creed, so that we can
recite the Rosary together whether we are at home, in school or in
church.

       Recite the other prayers to Mary like the Angelus and Memorare.
Ask for Mary’s Protection when you pray; We fly to your patronage O
Holy Mary, Mother of God.

Living our Faith

       Remind your parents, brothers and sisters to pray the rosary every
night before going to bed. When you pray the rosary in your classroom
with your classmates remind everyone to say the prayer slowly with love
and devotion. Show your love to Mary by respecting everyone while
praying.

       The Holy Church honors Virgin Mary, Mother of God, with a special
love. We make her a special person in our lives. We thank her being our
model. We ask her to help us faithfully follow Jesus Christ.]]></page><page Index="95"><![CDATA[Celebrating our Faith

1. Let us sing together this song:

       Queen of the Rosary, Mother of Mercy,
       Listen to thy children, who join to address thee.
       Teach us how to pray, lead us in a virtuous way,
       Virgin, Mother of Mercy,
       Queen of the Rosary, Most Blessed Lady
       Joyfully singing our homage we pay thee.
       Thou art our Mother dear, whom our true hearts
       revere, Virgin Mother, our Lady.
       Queen of the Rosary, Virgin the fairest,
       Blooming in paradise lily the rarest.
       Help us to persevere, blossom of virtue rare.
       Queen of Virgins, the fairest.

2. Let us recite the Holy Rosary.

Message from Marie Rivier

My dear children,

       Place all your trust in God and in the protection of the Blessed Virgin
Mary, our good Mother.]]></page><page Index="96"><![CDATA[UNIT 3

WE LIVE OUR FAITH

                              We are Members of the Church
                              We Live in the Presence of God]]></page><page Index="97"><![CDATA[WE LIVE OUR FAITH

       This unit focuses on the Moral Truths of our faith which include Man’s
Vocation, Ten Commendments, Persons and Society. The learners are led
to recognize, discern and commit to one’s vocation in life. They are
expected to know, interiorize and integrate the commandments in thesir
lives. They are challenged to engage in service and to exercise
responsible stewardship to the various communities to which they
belong: family, school, parish civic and global.

                             The Author

Marie Rivier, Woman of Zeal]]></page><page Index="98"><![CDATA[Lesson   Our Friend

 Jesus,    12

Expected Outcomes:
a. To explain why Jesus is our friend.
b. To show love and respect to friends and enemies.
c. To pray asking Jesus to forgive and love our enemies.

Life Situation

Who are your friends? Who are your enemies?
Story 1:

       Sheila and Annie are best friends. They live near each other in their
barrio. They come to school together. They help one another in making
their school work and assignments. They try their best to keep their
friendship lasting. They always think of how to help their classmates and
class adviser in school. Both of them are friendly to others.]]></page><page Index="99"><![CDATA[Story 2:
       Arden and Victor are cousins. They enjoyed going to the beach

every weekend with their other cousins, Eli and Samuel. One day their
enjoyment turned into misunderstanding. Eli had a fight with Arden while
Victor hurt James by kicking him. Their other cousins, Ralph and Rodulf
tried to pacify them. Their aunt Chita gave them advice, too. They all
realized their shortcomings and admitted their mistakes.

Values Development

In story one: What do you like in the friendship of Sheila and Annie?

In story two: What can you say about the friendship of the cousins,
                   Arden and Victor?

What lessons did you learn from the stories?
Who are your friends?
What kind of a friend are you?
Do you know that there is someone who is a friend of all?]]></page><page Index="100"><![CDATA[Proclamation of the Word of God

     Jesus went to the village of Bethany, not far from Jerusalem, as he
was invited by Mary and Martha who were sisters. Mary sat at Jesus
feet listening as he talked, while Martha hurried back and forth
preparing the food. After a while, she noticed that her sister was doing
nothing to help. “Is it right Lord that Mary should sit at your feet, while I
do all the work” she complained.” But Mary is wise, he gently told her.
“It is more important to listen to my teaching, as she does, than to worry
like you, about the affairs of the house. ”

     The two sisters had a brother called Lazarus, a little while after Jesus
had left. Lazarus fell seriously ill. Mary and Martha sent word to Jesus
begging him to come and save their brother’s life.

     The message reached Jesus as he was talking to his disciples.
“Lazarus is sleeping,” he said. “I will go and wake him. ” But he
remained where he was for several days before returning to Bethany.

     As he approached the sisters’ house, Martha, in tears ran out to
meet him. “If only I have been here Lord, my brother would have not
died!” “ Your brother shall rise from dead. You must have faith and
believe what I have taught you of the resurrection of the dead.”
Mary too, came out to Jesus weeping as if her heart would break.
When he saw the strength of her grief, he was deeply moved. ‘Where
has been Lazarus been laid?”]]></page><page Index="101"><![CDATA[He asked her. Accompanied by mourning relation, she led him to
 the tomb, which was in a cave, its mouth sealed by a heavy stone.
 “Take away the stone,” said Jesus. With difficulty the stone was rolled to
 one side. “Lazarus arise!” To everyone, Lazarus his head and body
 covered in white linen of his shroud, walked out of the cave. It was as
 Jesus said: “the dead man had been brought back to life, as if woken
 simply from sleep.”

                                                                                                              John 11:1- 44

       Jesus wanted Mary and Martha to profess their faith in Him. Martha
admitted that she believed that Jesus is the Son of God.

Where did Jesus go? Who invited him?
Who were the two sisters? Who was their brother?
What can you say about Mary? How about Martha?
What happened to Lazarus? What did Jesus do to him?
Who were the friends of Jesus?

Knowing our Faith

       Jesus is true God and true Man. In the human characteristic of
Jesus, He manifested His love for His friends, helping other and weeping
when He heard of the death of Lazarus. He spent His time on earth doing
good for bodies and souls. Because of His love for His Father and
mankind, He dedicated all His energies, His strength and His talents to the
service of souls. Many were indifferent to Him and even rejected Him.]]></page><page Index="102"><![CDATA[However, He continued to love and to draw them to Himself. He
manifested His great power raising His friend Lazarus, to life.

                                                                                                         My Catholic Faith

       Jesus is telling us that when we listen to the priests, teachers and
parents, we also listened to him.

       Many of us became friends of Jesus when we listened to Him. When
we commit sins and turn away from him we are not following him.
However, we must remember what Jesus said, “He who hears you, hears
me. He who rejects you, rejects me. And he who rejects me, rejects him
who sent me.”

We have to open our hearts to listen to Him because we need Him.]]></page><page Index="103"><![CDATA[Enhancing our Faith

       Jesus friends are those who believe in Him, work hard to spread the
Good News, who show their love for God by loving others.
Jesus has many enemies even today. There are still people who do not
believe in Him, and who work against His Church. But Jesus does not
condemn sinners instead He forgives them because of His great love for
all people.

        Tell what you like in the attitudes of Mary and Martha.
       Tell something about the story of Jesus and Lazarus.
       Relate why others criticized the work of Jesus.
       What kind of people are the friends of Jesus?

Living our Faith

       Make a project in “Card Making”. Select your companions or
friends whom you can work with. Provide your own materials like pens,
cartolina and crayons. Make cards and send to those who need friends
whether at home, in school and in the community or in your GKK.

Celebrating our Faith

       Everybody stand and take a partner and sing with action the song
below.

       Oh, I love you with love of the Lord.
       Yes I love you with the love of the Lord.
       I can see in you the glory of our Friend.
       Yes, I love you with the love of Jesus, our Friend.]]></page><page Index="104"><![CDATA[Let us pray:

       O Jesus, we see what great love you have for us and for others.
Help us to grow in our love for you. We can do things for others just
because we love you. Teach us to be more friendly to others as you are
a friend to us. We also pray for people who need to have friends.
Thank you for teaching us to forgive our neighbors as well as our enemies.
We have forgiven them. Amen.

Message from Marie Rivier

                             My dear children,

                               Think, speak and act like Jesus Christ. Never get
                        discourage of your faults, put your trust in God and love
Him as your Father.]]></page><page Index="105"><![CDATA[Lesson              Members of the Church

We are                               13
Active

Expected Outcomes:

a. To realize that God made us His children at Baptism.

b. To share in giving concern to the needs of the Church.

c. To thank God for the grace of His love received at Baptism.

Life Situation

                Mang Berto And His Three Children

Mang Berto had three children: Jolie, Josie and Joey. His wife died

long time ago due to severe illness. He managed to earn a living for his

family by working hard in the farm.]]></page><page Index="106"><![CDATA[One day, Mang Berto brought his children to their farm and made a
vegetable garden. Jolie tried to make plots and prepared the soil for
planting. Josie and Joey helped each other to prepare the seedlings.
Finally, they planted petchay, eggplants, tomatoes, raddish and lettuce
in their garden. Everyday the plants grew healthy because Mang Berto
and his children worked together and watered the plants in order to
produce good vegetables .

       Finally, after few months, the family of Mang Berto was happy
because many people came to ask for help because of scarcity of
food in their neighborhood.

       Mang Berto, Jolie, Josie and Joey were generous and kind to their
neighbors.

Value Development

Describe the family of Mang Berto.
What lessons did you learn from the short story?
What did Mang Berto and his children do to earn for their living?
How did the family express their love and concern to their neighbors?
Do you want to know more about how Jesus invite us to become active
members of His Church?

 Proclamation of the Word of God

       As the body is one, having many members, and all the members,
 while being many, from one body, so it is with Christ. All of us whether
 Jews or Greeks, slaves or free men, have been baptized in one Spirit to
 form one body and all of us have been given to drink from one spirit.]]></page><page Index="107"><![CDATA[The body is not one member, but many. Even through the foot
 says. I do not belong to the body for I am not a hand, “it continues to
 be part of the body. If all the body were eye, how would we hear?
 And if all the body were ear, how would we smell?

       God has arranged all the members, placing each part of the body
 as he pleased. If all were the same part where would the body be?
 But are many members and one body. The eye cannot tell the hand, I
 do not need you, nor do the head tell the feet, “I do not need you”.

       God himself arranged the body in this way, giving more honors to
 those parts that need it, so that the body may not be divided, but
 rather each member may care for the others. When one suffer, all of
 them suffer, and when it receives honour, all rejoices together.

       Now, you are the body of Christ and each of you individually is a
 member of it. So God has appointed us in the Church. First, Apostles;
 second, prophets; third, teachers; then come miracles, then the gift of
 healing, material help, administration in the Church and the gifts of
 tongues.

                                                                                                         1 Cor. 12: 12 – 28

       The Church is made up of many people with different talents,
cultures and characteristics. But Jesus makes us one in the spirit of unity.
Every member has something to contribute to make the Church grow.]]></page><page Index="108"><![CDATA[Now, we belong to the body of Christ.
       What does the word body refer to?
       Who belong to the body of Christ?
       What must we do to other members of Christ’s body?

Knowing our Faith

       Jesus was sent by His Heavenly Father to live among us to bring us
all back to His Father in the family of God.

       Jesus did not finish His work while He lived on earth. But today, He
is doing it through us, and through other people in the Church.

       The Church is the new people of God. It is not just a building but the
family of God.

       When people were baptized, the Holy Spirit was given
to them to make them share in love and strength of Jesus, so that they
will be able to help Jesus in His great work.

       We are one of these people of God who became active members
of the Church after we received Baptism.

       The Church is a sign of God’s love and presence. Jesus is present
among us through the Holy Spirit. Jesus gathers together all baptized
people to worship and praise God for His goodness.

Challenges of our Faith

       The apostles were sent into far countries to spread the Good News
of God’s love and many people listened and asked to be baptized to
belong to God’s family.]]></page><page Index="109"><![CDATA[We are aware that each sacrament is a personal meeting with
Christ and an expression of love and we receive grace.

       In the sacrament of Baptism, we receive God’s life to help us live in
the family of God and make us active member to help others come into
God’s kingdom.

       All of us are created by God. Each of us has our own dignity as a
person with different opinions, feeling and ideas. However, if we love and
respect others we have to learn to respect their opinions and ideas and
we will be united in making the Church grow in the love of God.

       There are times and moments of disagreement and discontentment
but we strive to preserve unity by acknowledging the contribution of
others through their time, talents and service in the Church.

       We can be like the apostles and help others to know the goodness
and love of God.

       We should be proud to profess our faith to keep the family of God
growing by living as true children of God.

       Let us remember to be one with God when we attend the Mass
faithfully and receive the sacraments regularly.

       Because we are God’s children possessing His life, then, the likeness
of God will show in our attitudes, words and actions. We are given the
power to act like Christ.

Enhancing our Faith

       At baptism we receive God’s light, life and love. We must have
God’s life and love in our souls if we believe that everyone wants to live
with God forever.]]></page><page Index="110"><![CDATA[Color the drawing. Write a story below it.

_______________________________________________________________________
_______________________________________________________________________
_______________________________________________________________________
_______________________________________________________________________
_______________________________________________________________________
_________________________________________

Living our Faith

       We should help pray that priests, religious and lay people who work
to bring people to God will have the same fire of love as the Apostles.

       We should also pray for ourselves and all members of our family,
relatives and friends so that we all become active members of the
Church and true believers who love God. We need to give our time in
praising God together with the other members of the Church.]]></page><page Index="111"><![CDATA[Celebrating our Faith

Let us sing together this song:
       Holy Spirit Come, make my eyes to see.
       Make my ears to hear; make my mouth to speak.
       Make my heart to feel and my hands to reach out.
       And touch the world with Your love.

Let us pray together:
       Lord God,
       Thank You for the Church You have given us.
       Thank You for bringing us together as Your family.
       Thank You, Lord for being our God. Amen.

Message from Marie Rivier

My dear children,

       I expect everything from everyone to learn from what Jesus told us
that we believe in Someone who sent Him. He did the work of His Father

                    for the salvation of souls.]]></page><page Index="112"><![CDATA[Lesson              to God Through His

We Commandments

Becom               14
e Close

Expected Outcomes:

a. To tell the two great commandments which are to love God and to

love others.

b. To show our joy when we worship God and love others.

c. To pray that the people of God will obey the commandments

faithfully.

Life Situation

       Dramatize the various types of rules that people are expected to
keep.]]></page><page Index="113"><![CDATA[Group 1 – What are some rules in your family? It could be the time for
                 going to bed or rising or time for meals.

Group II – What are some rules in your school? It could be the time in
                 coming to school or during class hours or in going home.

Group III – What are some rules for sports and games? It could be how
                 to play basketball, or volleyball or softball.

Group IV – What are some traffic rules? It could be following the light
                 signal when to stop or go or to cross the street using the
                 pedestrian lane.

Value Development

Why do parents give rules at home?
Why do teachers give rules in school?
Why do referees give rules in games?
Why do traffic men give traffic rules?

       Do you want to know how God gave us His laws? Why did God give
rules or laws that we should keep?]]></page><page Index="114"><![CDATA[Proclamation of the Word of God

       One of the scribes came up to Jesus, and asked him. “Which is the
 first of all commandments?” Jesus replied: This is the first: “Hear O Israel!
 The Lord God is Lord alone! Therefore you shall love the Lord your God
 with all you heart, with all your soul, with all your mind and with all your
 strength.” This is the second: “you shall love your neighbor as yourself.
 There is no other commandment greater than these.” The scribe said to
 him: “Excellent, Teacher! You are right in saying, He is the One, there is
 not other than he. Yes. To love him with all our heart, with all our
 thoughts and with all our strength and to love our neighbor as
 ourselves is worth more than any burnt offering of sacrifice.” Jesus
 approved the insight of this answer and told him, “You are not far from
 the reign of God.” And no one had the courage to ask him any more
 questions.

                                                                                                          Mark 12: 28 – 34

       All the commandments of God are great and important. The
greatest commandment is love, and it is found in all the Ten
Commandments. If we say we love God, then we must love our
neighbor. If we truly love our neighbor, then we want our neighbor to
enjoy everything that is good.

What are the two great commandments of God?
How do we love God?
How do we love our neighbors?]]></page><page Index="115"><![CDATA[Knowing our Faith

       God our Father made us in love. He made us so that we could one
day enjoy a life of love with Him in heaven. He has given us laws that we
call the TEN COMMANDMENTS. Some of there laws tell us what to do;
some tell us what to avoid. The first three commandments tell us how to
love God; the other seven tell us how to love ourselves and others.

                                   The Ten Commandments

  1. I am the Lord your God. You shall not have other God besides me.
  2. You shall not take the name of the Lord your God in vain.
  3. Remember to keep holy the Sabbath Day.
  4. Honor your father and your mother.
  5. You shall not kill.
  6. You shall not commit adultery.
  7. You shall not steal.
  8. You shall not bear false witness against your neighbor.
  9. You shall not covet your neighbors’ wife.
10. You shall not covet anything that belongs to your

      neighbor.

                                                                        Deuteronomy 5:6 – 12

       God our Father gave us the Ten Commandments
out of love for us. The Ten Commandments help us to give ourselves to
God in love, and finally to attain heaven and be with Him forever.

       As creatures, we owe God love and obedience. God revealed
Himself to us to help know Him, love Him and serve Him. So, to respond to
our Father’s love we keep His Commandments.

Jesus taught us that all the laws are contained in two great laws:
1. Love God with all your heart, with all your soul, with all your strength,

     and with all your mind.
2. Love your neighbor as yourself.]]></page><page Index="116"><![CDATA[Challenges of our Faith

       God gave us His commandments to help us. They tell us how to love
God by adoring and worshiping Him, by speaking to Him often, by
offering Sacrifice to Him. They tell us what it means to love other people;
to be kind to them, to respect their life and their property, and to pray for
them.

       The commandments help us to give good examples to others in all
that we do and say.

       We call God our Heavenly Father. We speak His name with love
and respect. We praise the name of the Lord together when we pray
and sing at Mass.

       When we say the name of Jesus, we can think of Him teaching,
healing, suffering or dying.

       On Sundays many of us, as children of God joined together in our
parish church to attend the Eucharistic Celebration.

       We invite the members of our family, friends and neighbors to
participate in the celebration in the church to experience peace, love,
and joy in the Lord.

       We keep Gods’ laws to obey our parents and elders. God wants us
to use our bodies for work and play, for working and praying, for being
good to our neighbors and towards other people.

       We must respect everything that belong to others and return to the
owner things that belong to them. God wants us to be honest with
ourselves and with others.

       We are sometimes afraid to tell the truth about something we have
done, because we are afraid that telling the truth will bring us a
punishment.

       We must learn from the examples of Jesus on how to speak and act
truthfully.]]></page><page Index="117"><![CDATA[Enhancing our Faith

Remember how God gave the commandments to Moses when He was
preparing the world for the coming of our Savior.

What do the first three commandments tell us about?

How about the other seven commandments?

What are the Ten Commandments that help us to give good examples
to others in all that we do and say?

Living our Faith

       The Ten Commandments are signposts that help us to love the laws
of love.

1. Make a poster with drawing on how you show something that is
     helpful to guide others, at home, in school or in church by obeying
     the commandments of God.

2. Select a place where you can display your poster; at home, in school
     or in church.

Celebrating our Faith

Let us pray together:

       O God, help us to know you so that we can love You. Help us to
love You so that we will learn to serve you always.]]></page><page Index="118"><![CDATA[O God, you are good to us. You gave us the Ten Commandments
to help up us on our way to heaven. Let us try hard every day to listen
and learn more about them. Let us not forget to love God and to love
others.
Let us sing together this song: Prayer of St. Francis

1. Make me a channel of your peace.
       Where there is hatred let me bring Your love.
       When there is injury, Your pardon Lord.
       And when there’s doubt , true faith in You.

2. Make me a channel of Your peace.
       When there’s despair in life let me bring hope.
       Where there’s darkness, only light.
       And when there’s sadness ever joy.
       Chorus: Oh Master, grant that I may never seek.
                           So much to be consoled as to console.
                           To be understood as to understand.
                                 To be loved as to love with all my soul.

3. Make me a channel of Your peace.
       It is in pardoning that we are pardoned.
       In giving to all men that we received,
       And in dying that we’re born to eternal life.

Message from Marie Rivier

                             My dear children,

                               To obey God’s laws is to depend only on Jesus
                        Christ, act according to His spirit and do all for His love.]]></page><page Index="119"><![CDATA[Lesson  from the Heart

 We 15

  Help

Expected Outcomes:
a. To realize that one must love God and help others to get to heaven.
b. To show how to be loving and caring to those who are in pain and

     sorrow.
c. To pray for the conversion of sinners and the spiritual needs of our

     neighbor.

Life Situation

                                   We are Followers of Jesus
       We must remember that we always want to be strong and faithful
members of God’s family. What should we do? It means we have to
make some little sacrifices to become the real Apostles of Jesus.

Group yourselves according to your special work on how to help

others and dramatize it.]]></page><page Index="120"><![CDATA[Group 1 – teacher, guidance counselor, pupil
               Group 2 – priest, people of God in GKK
               Group 3 – a family that lost a father,
               Group 4 – a friend needing someone’s advice
               Group 5 – a policeman with a quarrelsome boy

Value Development

Show how you bring out what you could do to others who need your
help.

Can you think of some things you could have given up for someone who
is in sorrow?

How do you feel while you are presenting the special work to your
classmate?

Where you able to do something from the heart?

What must you do to follow the laws of God?

       How can you bring out what Jesus, our leader does for us?
What special help does Jesus do to his apostles?

 Proclamation of the Word of God

       Before the feast of Passover, Jesus realized that the hour come for
 him to pass from this world to the Father. He had loved his own in this
 world, and would show his love for them to the end. The devil had
 already induced Judas, son of Simon Iscariot, to hand Jesus over; and
 so, during the supper, Jesus was fully aware that he had come from
 God and was going to God, the Father, who had handed everything
 over to him, rose from the meal and took off his cloak.]]></page><page Index="121"><![CDATA[He picked up a towel and tied it around himself. He poured water
 into a basin and began to wash his disciples’ feet and dry the, with the
 towel he had around him. Thus he came to Simon Peter, who said to
 him, “Lord, are you going to wash my feet?” Jesus answered, “You may
 not realize now what I am doing, but later you will understand. Peter
 replied, “You shall never wash my feet! If I do not wash you,” Jesus
 answered, “You will have no share in my heritage,” Lord’ Simon Peter
 said to him “then only my feet but my hands and head as well,” Jesus
 told him, “the man who has bathed has no need to wash except for his
 feet; he is entirely cleaned just as you are through at all,” the reason he
 said, “not all are washed clean,” was that he knew his betrayer.

        After he had washed their feet, he put his cloak back on and reclined
  at table once more. He said to them. “Do you understand what I just did
  for you? You address me as Teacher and Lord, and fittingly enough, for
  that is what I am. But if I wash your feet - I who am Teacher and Lord, then
  you must wash each other’s feet. What I just did was to give you an
  example: as I have done, so you must do.”

                                                                                                             Luke 13: 1 – 15

What did Jesus do to His twelve apostles?
How did Jesus show to His apostles that He serve from the heart?
Why did He wash the feet of His apostles?
Were they all contented on what Jesus did to them?
What did Jesus say after He washed the feet of His apostles?
What message did you learn?]]></page><page Index="122"><![CDATA[Knowing our Faith

       To love God, our neighbor and ourselves, we must keep the
commandments of the Church and perform the spiritual works of mercy
to relieve the spiritual needs of our neighbor. We help them from the
heart.
The Spiritual Works of Mercy are:

1. Pray for the conversion of sinners.
2. Teach the ignorant.
3. Advice the doubtful.
4. Give comfort for those who are in sorrow.
5. Bear difficulties with patience.
6. Forgive those who hurt you.
7. Pray for the living and the dead.

                                                                                                         My Catholic Faith

       Everyone is obliged to perform the works of mercy accordingly to
his own ability and the need of his neighbors.

Challenges of our Faith

       Every act or work done in the name of or for the sake of Christ is a
work of mercy, and will be rewarded in heaven. Caring for others is a
way of recognizing that they, too, are loved by God.

       Parents and teachers are bound to give advice to those who are
under their care. However, as children of God, we can also teach others
by giving good examples. We must do so with gentleness and love.]]></page><page Index="123"><![CDATA[We are called to give comfort to those who are in sorrow, those
who are sad and those who are worried. We help them by giving
consolations and by guiding them in their spiritual needs.

       In their times of troubles and difficult life, our neighbors and the
poor need us. Let us be patient with them in justice. Our patience helps
them realize their wrong-doing. Let us be kind to them.

       We must forgive others, as we hope God will forgive us. Let us not
take revenge, instead let us imitate the saints who go out of their way to
do favors to those who injure them.

       We pray for the living and the dead. We may not see the effects of
our prayers but God sees. Not one single prayer raised to God from a
sincere heart is wasted. Let us grow strong in our faith through prayer.

We must give support and encourage those who need our help.

Enhancing our Faith

A. What are the spiritual works of mercy?

       1. _________________________________

       2. _________________________________

       3. _________________________________

       4. _________________________________

       5. _________________________________

       6. _________________________________

       7. _________________________________]]></page><page Index="124"><![CDATA[B. Fill in the blanks with correct letters

       C __ m f __ r t

       K __ n d n __ s s

       H __ l p

       C __ __ r __ g __

       F __ r g __ v __

Living our Faith

Draw your answer in each box.

1. Show 1 act of kindness to people at home.]]></page><page Index="125"><![CDATA[2. Help your classmate who needs your comfort.
3. Show to your friends that you forgive them.]]></page><page Index="126"><![CDATA[Celebrating our Faith

Let us pray together:

       Heavenly Father, help all those who work in Your vineyard especially
those who promise to give support to our neighbors through their act of
kindness and merciful acts.

       Help us also to comfort those who are in sorrow, give advice to
those who are confused.

       Fill our hearts with Your wisdom and power so that we may lead
others towards Your heavenly kingdom.

Message from Marie Rivier

My dear children,

          The Heart of Jesus is a heart of love, a heart of fire and a furnace
of charity for the whole human race.]]></page><page Index="127"><![CDATA[Lesson              Serve

We Are              16
Sent to

Expected Outcomes:

a. To realize that one must love God and help others to get to heaven.

b. To show how to be loving and caring to those who are in pain and

sorrow.

c. To pray for the conversion of sinners and the spiritual needs of our

neighbor.

Life Situation

Dramatize how to help others based from the story below.

                    To Serve is to Love

Norman and Teddy are good friends. One Sunday afternoon they

went to the house of their friend, Johnny. Before reaching the house,

they saw Johnny welcoming them with a sad face. When they arrived

they went inside the house and found the mother of Johnny very weak

because she got sick for almost a month.

       Norman ran to their neighbor and asked for help
while Teddy went back to their house and asked his parents to help the
sick mother of his friend.]]></page><page Index="128"><![CDATA[Many came to visit the sick mother and they left
after saying a prayer for the complete recovery of the mother of Johnny.
After a while, Norman came back with a companion and they took the
sick mother to the doctor. Teddy brought an ambulance and asked his
father to bring the sick mother to the hospital but after they consulted
the doctor on their way home the mother of Johnny died.

Value Development

How did Norman and Teddy offer their service to the sick mother of
Johnny?

How would you feel if you are in the place of Johnny?

How do you feel when you share your time with others?

What happens to your sick neighbor if no one could help?

Why are we made for service?

In what way can we make an act of kindness?

 Proclamation of the Word of God

             Jesus said to his disciples, “when the Son of Man comes and
 before him will be gathered all the nations, and he will separate them
 one from another, as the shepherd separates the sheep from the
 goats; and he will set the sheep on his right hand, but the goats on the
 left.” Then the king will say to those on his right hand, “Come, blessed of
 my father, take possession of]]></page><page Index="129"><![CDATA[the Kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world; for I
was hungry and you gave me to eat; I was thirsty and you gave me
drink; I was stranger and you took me in; naked and you covered me;
sick and you visited me, I was in prison and you came to me.” Then the
just will answer him saying, “Lord when did we see you hungry and feed
you, or thirsty and give you drink? And when did we see you stranger,
and take you in; or naked and clothe you? Or when did we see you
sick; or in prison, and come to you?” And answering, the king will say to
them, “Amen. I say to you as long as you did it for one of these, the
least of my brethren, you did it for me.”

                                      Matt 25: 32 – 40

What did Jesus say to his disciples?

What message did you learn?

What was Jesus trying to tell us?

What will you do if you are in the place of Jesus?

Knowing our Faith

       We should all know that there are works of mercy that God wants us
to do for our neighbors.

       They deserve all the help that we can give. Jesus asks us to give
attention to the poor and the needy, to the sufferings and all victims of
calamities. These are the acts of kindness that we should do.]]></page><page Index="130"><![CDATA[The Corporal Works of Mercy are:

1. Feed the hungry.               Challenges of
2. Give drink to the thirsty.     our Faith
3. Shelter the homeless.
4. Cloth the naked.
5. Comfort the sick.
6. Visit those in prison.
7. Bury the dead.

My Catholic Faith

       Corporal works of mercy are those that God wants
us to do for our neighbors. When we are doing something
good for others, we are doing it for the love of God.

       We are performing an act of charity to the poor especially when
we provide them food when they come to us and ask for help.
Sometimes we turn away from those who beg for help but we can do our
best in giving them work than direct alms-giving.

       We can ask for help from the responsible people who can provide
ways and means in giving drink to those who are thirsty.]]></page><page Index="131"><![CDATA[We are encouraged to give clothes to the needy and poor, to the
beggars and who have nothing to wear due to natural calamities like
victims of fire and floods.

       We are asked to do works of mercy by visiting prisoners in jail,
helping their families, and assisting their families especially the poor.
There are many times when we meet people who are dirty especially
those who are staying under the bridge. Can we afford to provide them
homes for shelter for they do not have a place where to stay?

       Many of us are aware of the situation of people who are in need of
medicines. If we cannot afford to give any perhaps we can have a little
sacrifice to visit the sick like those who are all in the hospitals or our
nearby neighbors like the evacuees and other victims of calamities.

Enhancing our Faith

Jesus wants us to help the needy and those who are sufferings.

       Every person needs the help we can give. Jesus teaches us to help
others not only those who are good to us but even those who are against
us. Everybody is created by God in His own image and likeness.

       Memorize the act of kindness that you do to the least of our
brothers:

1. Provide food for the hungry.
2. Give drink to the thirsty,
3. __________________________
4. __________________________
5. __________________________
6. __________________________
7. __________________________]]></page><page Index="132"><![CDATA[Living our Faith

       Which of the corporal works of mercy do you need to do right away
when you go home?

Visit your sick neighbor.
Gather the old clothes and give to the Caritas.
Share some food to the beggars.

       What other acts of kindness could you offer when you are in school?

How about in the community?

How will you help the victims of calamities?

Celebrating our Faith

Let us sing together this song:

Chorus: Whatsoever you do to the least of my brothers. That you do unto
            me.

1. When I was hungry, you gave me to eat.
        When I was thirsty, you give me to drink.
        Now enter into the home of my Father. (cho.)

2. When I was homeless, you opened your door.
        When I was naked, you gave me your coat.
       Now enter into the home of my Father. (cho.)

3. When I was weary, you help me find rest.
       When I was anxious, you calmed all my tears.
       Now enter in to the home of my Father. (cho.)]]></page></pages></Search>