<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="190"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[SOURCES OF OUR FAITH

God’s Presence In His Creation]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[SOURCES OF OUR FAITH

    This unit focuses on the Revelation of God, Sacred Tradition and
Sacred Scripture. The learners are introduced to the Sources of Faith of
the Catholic Church. They gradually become convinced that Sacred
Tradition is not the only way to know God for their holiness and
salvation. This is a great treasure of the Church that must be adhered
to and kept. The learners are introduced to read and understand the
Sacred Scripture as God’s Word speaking to them. The learners also
need to know and understand the basic teachings of the Church and
how these apply in their lives.

                                                                                      The Author

                                                         Marie Rivier, Woman Apostle]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Lesson1

                               Expected Outcomes:
                               a. To realize that God made all
                               things beautiful to make us happy.

b. To respect God’s creation.
c. To praise
and thank
God for the
things around
us.

                                       Beauty of Nature

One day Nympha went with her mother to the river. They enjoyed
looking at the flowing of the clear and clean water. Nympha wanted
to go fishing but her mother stopped her. She followed what the
mother told her. Then she said, “I don’t know how to swim. So, I’ll better
sit on the big rock and watch the beautiful things around.”]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Her mother just walked along the bank of the river
gathering firewood while Nympha was left behind by
herself. As Nympha looked around the beautiful creation, she can’t
help but sing.

             When her mother came back, Nympha was singing
happily while gathering the little flowers at the riverbank.

               “There was a little turtle, who lived in a box. He swam
            with his paddles. He climbed on the rock. He snapped at

                                           the mosquito,
                           He snapped at the flea.

                              He snapped at the minnow and he
                            snapped at me.”

                Then, she sang another song; looking at the sky.

                      “
                      T
                      w
                      i
                      n
                      k
                      l
                      e
                      ,

                        twinkle little star, How I wonder what you
                        are. Up above the world so high, Like the
                         diamond in the sky. Twinkle, twinkle little

                             star, How I wonder what you are.”

      Nympha and her mother were happy. They thanked God for the
wonderful creations.]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[What made Nympha sing?
                                                         Why was Nympha happy?
                                                         What made her mother
happy?
Who created those things that made them happy? Do you want to
      know why God made all these beautiful

things for us?]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[We learn to know about God from the world He has created. He
made the wonderful creation to make us happy.

                                                             We know about God
                                                         when we see the wonders
                                                         of His creation.
    God made the world and everything in it for us. He made the world
to show His power, wisdom and love. He made it for us to care, to use
and to be happy.
    How great God is in His beautiful creation. The sun keeps us warm.
The moon and stars make the night beautiful, and there are many
other creatures that we see around which made us happy.

    God alone created the universe freely, directly and without any help.

                                                                                            CCC 317]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[When God made the world
                                                            everything became useful.

                                                                 He made the sun to
give us heat. It helps us to dry our clothes.

    He gave us water to drink and to help the plants and animals
grow.

    When God finished creating the world, all things became
very good.

    God wants us to use all things He made for us to be happy.
We should take good care of them.]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[God speaks to us through His
                                                          creation. Activity: Planting
seeds -Divide the pupils into small group.
-Ask each group to bring seed and soil in a small pot. -(The
following day) Let each group plant the seed in a small pot and
ask them to water it everyday until it grows.

Enjoy the beauty of nature. Thank You God for this beautiful world.]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Through God’s creation we live
                               by getting food from animals,
                               plants, fish, trees, and from other
                               creatures. We also have flowers to

beautify our church and home.

    Only God can make us strong and healthy through the food He
provides for us.

    We must take care of the plants around us. We water them every

day.

    We must also take good care of the animals like our pet dogs and
cats. We give them food every day.

We help our parents at home to clean our surroundings.]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[We say a little prayer,

                                                               O, God, You are so
                                                               wonderful. Thank You, God
    for our wonderful world. We know that everything comes from You.
    Everything is good. Help us to take care of everything You made.
    Amen.

    Let us sing this song to praise God for the wonderful things
around us.

GOD IS      SO GOOD, GOD IS SO GOOD,
GOD IS    SO GOOD, HE IS SO GOOD TO US.

In the    name of the Father, and of the
Son, and  of the Holy Spirit. Amen.]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Lesson2

Expected Outcomes:
a. To tell that the Bible is one way of getting to know God.
b. To show respect and love for the written Word of God.
c. To pray and thank God for His message of love in the Holy Bible.

When we listen to people, we use our ears. When we watch how they
act, we use our eyes. God has given us our senses to communicate
with Him and to other people.

          Listen to the conversation of few pupils on how
   they communicate with one another. Tony: I use my
   eyes to see God and His creation. Timy: I use my ears to
   listen about God. Leny: I use my voice to speak about
   God. Zeny: I use my hands to do things for God and]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[others.]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Remy: I use my feet to go to the Church. Beny: I use my mind to think
about God. Rony: I use my heart to love God and others.

How do they talk to one another? What will happen if they don’t listen
                                                         to one another?

                                                             Today, we will think of how
                                                         we help others to know and
                                                         love God better.
a. Who are those people who speak to us about God? (Our parents,
teachers, priests, nuns and others)
b. Who are those community helpers who can teach us about God by
what they do?
    (Doctors, Nurses, Policemen, Firemen, and people who visit the
    sick.)
c. Do you want to know more about God?
    (The more we know God the more we will love and serve Him)]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Who are the two sons of Adam and Eve? What made the offering of
Abel pleasing to God? What did Cain do to his brother, Abel?Why?
How did God show his love to Abel and Cain? What will happen if we
do not know how to love?]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[We need to know more about
                                                     God through the Bible. The
                                                     Bible is a way of getting to
                                                     know God better.
    This book is the Holy Bible. It is a special book that

teaches us about God. In the Holy Bible we find the story of
God’s love for each one of us.

    There are two main parts of the Bible The first part is called the OLD
TESTAMENT. In it, we learn about creation, how man sinned, and God’s
promise to send the savior. We also learn how God prepared men for
the coming of His Son, Jesus our Savior. The second part is called the
NEW TESTAMENT. It tells about the life and mission of Jesus, His words
and actions. He says and does many things to lead us to His Father.

    The Bible is a Holy book because it is the Word of God. It comes to
us from God. The Holy Spirit helped certain people to write it and the
Holy Spirit helps us to understand it.]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[We learn about God in
                                             many ways.

                                             We learn about God

from the beautiful world He created for us.

We learn about God from people who tell us about Him.

    We can also learn about God from the example of people
who live and act as Jesus did.

    There are times when we do not understand the written Word of
God. So we ask the Holy Spirit to help enlighten our minds.

    We give importance to the Holy Bible. We find the Bible readings
selected for each day in the lectionary. We give reverence to the
Bible and all books which contain the Word of God. When the priests
or lay readers read the message of God, it is God speaking to us.

Q. Why do we say that the Bible is the most important book?

A. It teaches us about God.

Q. What does it tell us?

A. In the Old Testament, it tells us about God’s creation and God’s
    promise to send us the savior. In the New Testament, it tells us about
    the life of Jesus, His words and actions. He says many things to lead
    us to His Father.]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Make the following diagram and draw lines:

                                  The Holy Bible
    We should always remember that God’s plan and laws from the
beginning of the world have been written down in the Holy Bible.
    When we read the Bible it is God’s Holy Word which we should
love and respect.
We must handle the Bible with love and respect.
    We can learn God’s message when we read His words in the Holy
Bible.
We hear the Word of God when we go to Mass in the church.]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Let us have a Bible Enthronement inside our classroom. One pupil will
    carry the Holy Bible and two pupils will be the candle bearers.

    Let us have a procession around the room to a place of
enthronement. Let us sing:

Enter rejoice and come in Open our hearts to the Lord Today will be
                                      our joyful day Enter rejoice and come in.]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Psalm Prayer: Let our response be:

Glory and praise to you, O Lord, Jesus Christ

1. Give thanks to the Lord for he is good, his love is everlasting Let the
   house of Israel say His love is everlasting. (Response)

2. I called to the Lord in my distress he answered and freed me The
   Lord is at my side, I do not fear What can man do against me.
   (Response)

3. You are my Lord, I give you thanks I extol you, my God; I give you
   thanks for having heard me You have been my savior. (Response)

    Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit, As it was in
    the beginning is now and ever shall be world without end. Amen.]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Lesson3

Expected
Outcomes:
a. To be aware
that God chose
Moses to do a
special task;
b. To show
faithfulness in
doing one’s
work patiently;
and
c. To pray that
God will help us in everything we are asked to do.

Picture Viewing Describe the picture of Moses below.]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[God knows each one of us. He
                                                     calls us by name. We are all
important to Him. It is polite to call people by their names. What will you
do when your name is called? How do you answer when you are
called? What will you expect when someone calls you?]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Moses was the man chosen by God to a special mission. When he
was a newly born child, his mother hid him because Pharaoh ordered
his men to kill all newly born boys. When her mother cannot anymore
hide him, she put him in the basket and put it in the river. He was saved
by the daughter of Pharaoh from the water and later became the]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[leader of his people who were slaves in Egypt. When God called Moses
to lead the Chosen People from the land of Egypt to the Promised
Land, He felt he could not do what God wanted. But God assured him
that his brother, Aaron will help him. Moses trusted and obeyed God.]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[When Moses asked the permission of Pharaoh, the ruler of the
Egyptians that his people will leave Egypt, he would not listen to Moses.
God help him, then, by sending ten plagues to the Egyptians. Finally,
the chosen people were led out of the slavery of Egypt but hardships
continued as God made them wander in the desert for forty years.
They suffered hunger and thirst but God miraculously took care of
them by giving them bread from heaven, bringing forth water from a
rock and sending flocks of quail.

    God watched over His chosen People carefully even when they
were still slaves in Egypt. God saw the sufferings of His people, that’s
why He called Moses to free them. God was with them as they
journeyed from Egypt to the promise land.

    God watches over us also. He wants us to learn good things from
others, not bad things. If we commit sins we become slaves of the
devil. So we take courage to say at times, “Oh God, teach me to
follow your ways. Keep me far away from sin and protect me from
temptations.”

    We know that sometimes we do the wrong thing. We know that it is
wrong to disobey God and hurt anyone else like Abraham’s
descendants who became God’s Chosen People. God has many
plans for them but in the beginning, they disobeyed Him, and turned
away from Him. These people knew the difference between right and
wrong because God put his knowledge in their hearts. But they did
what pleased them.]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Recall the short story of Moses
                                                       before the burning bush.
                                                       Complete the drawing by
                                                       following the broken lines.
When God called Moses, at first, he was afraid. He thought he would

not be able to do the work God had given him. But God told him not to
be afraid and He said, “I will be with you always.”]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[We must also remember that when our parents will tell us what to do
we should not be afraid because they are with us, always helping ,
protecting and guiding us in whatever we do whether at home or in

                                                               school.

           We must do our work
           faithfully with love and

patience.

    When we follow our parents, we also follow what God wants us to
do.

Let us say together this prayer:

      “With all my heart I will seek You O God. Let me not lose hope in
     you. I am happy to do what you want me to do. May I follow your
     footsteps and obey your commands.”

         Our Father……… Glory be ………..]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[Lesson4

Expected Outcomes:
a. To realize that John
the Baptist had been chosen to prepare the way of the Lord;
b. To give importance in asking for the gift of forgiveness;
c. To pray to God to help us in all we must do.

                                          Here We Are

    One day, Mrs. Tamayo received a phone call from her husband
that the Mayor of their town will visit them. Right after she was informed
of the coming of the most important person in their town, Mrs. Tamayo
prepared everything in their house. She assigned her eldest son, Makki
to clean]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[their surroundings while the eldest daughter, Betsy, prepared the
visitor’s room including the living room. The family of Mr. and Mrs.
Tamayo was excited to receive their visitor. Something special was
prepared which was different from the way they received their other
visitors. Everyone was excited for the coming of their visitor.

It is our practice at home that when someone is
coming to visit us we prepare something special.
What would you do when your visitor is coming?
How would you prepare? Why do you need to
prepare before the coming of your visitor? What
happens if you do not prepare?]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[Long before Jesus was
                                                         born, there was a man
                                                         named Zechariah and he
                                                         had a wife named Elizabeth.
They were childless, for Elizabeth was sterile and both were
advanced in years. But both were just in the eyes of God, faithfully
following the commandments of God.

    One day, when Zechariah was offering in the temple, the angel told
him that his wife will have a baby and be filled with the Holy Spirit. At
first, Zechariah did not believe. So the Angel told him, “Because you
doubted, you would not be able to speak until the baby was born.”

    The day came when the baby was to be given a name; they asked
Zechariah if the baby would be named after him. So Zechariah wrote
on a piece of paper that the baby shall be named John and from that
moment he could talk again. John grew up to be a strong man.

    Elizabeth, his mother was the cousin of Mary, the Mother of Jesus.
Therefore, John the Baptist and Jesus were cousins.

    John, the Baptist lived mostly in the desert and ate only
grasshoppers and wild honey. He wore a coat of camel hair. He
prepared the way for Jesus by proclaiming to the people a life of
repentance because a Redeemer is coming soon. He had a very
special mission to prepare the people for the Savior. John knew that
the time was near when the people would be saved.]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[We learned that John
                                                            prepared the people by
                                                            preaching and telling them
                                                            about the coming of the
Saviour. He wanted the people to turn away from their sins. John the
Baptist tried to convince people to repent with all their hearts and
minds.

    How about us? What would we do when we committed sins?Do we
ask for forgiveness to the people whom we hurt? Before we go to bed
in the evening what would we say to Jesus? Do we also ask forgiveness
to Jesus of the mistakes we did during the day or we immediately sleep
without talking to Jesus?

    We will try to make it a habit to say sorry if we had done wrong at
home especially to our parents and members of our family. We ask for
forgiveness and tell God that we are sorry for all our sins.]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[John the Baptist was the
                                                          last messenger that God sent
                                                          to prepare the people for the
                                                          Savior.

       John lived in the _________________ and ate only
____________________ and ____________ John the Baptist proclaimed
a baptism of ________________________.

       John said “I baptize you with ____________ but someone who is
    more powerful than I will come to baptize you with the
    ______________________________________________.

                                                           By this time, you are getting
                                                       ready to receive Jesus in the
                                                       Holy Communion. All of us are
                                                       eager to receive Jesus in our
                                                       hearts.

    But how should we prepare ourselves in order to receive Jesus
worthily? Let us prepare for the coming of Jesus into our life by
preparing our hearts and minds.

    Let us listen attentively to our parents at home and to our teachers
in school and always ask sorry for our misdeeds.]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[Before we go to bed tonight, let us remember all what we did
especially the wrong we have done, and say an act of forgiveness to
Jesus.

    Let us learn to work faithfully when we are given special
assignment by our parents and teachers.

Dear Lord God,

      Today I learned many good lessons. I know sometimes I have
done some mistakes. I make you sad when I do wrong. Help me clean
my heart. I am sorry. Forgive me. Let me forgive those who have hurt
me. Forgive them, too.

      Help me to follow the example of Jesus, your Son, who lives and
reigns forever and ever. Amen.]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[Lesson

                                                   Expected Outcomes:
                                                   a. To discuss the second part of the
                                                   Bible that tells us the words and
                                                   actions of Jesus.
b. To be grateful for God’s love for us.
c. To say a prayer of praise.

      What do you do at home after you finished your supper?Do
you asked your Lolo or Lola to tell you some interesting
stories?What kind of stories are they?

      Everyone loves to listen to stories. Young and old alike are
interested to tell what they heard and what they have seen. All of us
learned to read stories to teach others especially the young people.

      Stories tell us many things. They can teach you about the world,
about people in other countries or about our environment. Stories
help you remember people who took care of you and those who
love you.

      Your parents or grandparents told you many stories from the book
or from the television. They also used stories to teach you about Jesus
and His wonderful deeds. This book where they get the stories about
Jesus is called the Bible.]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[Would you like to share with us
                               a story you heard from your Lola

or from your parents at home?

(One or two pupils will be asked.)
Do you like the story related by your classmate?
What lesson did you learn from it?
What kind of stories do you like most?
Where do you get those stories?

How do stories help us?]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[What did Jesus tell his apostles? What happened to the apostles? Why
were they afraid? How did Jesus save them?

                                                         37]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[The New Testament brings
                                                     Christ close to us. You hear His
                                                     words and see His actions. We are
                                                     eager to be like Jesus when we
hear him in the stories from the Bible.
                                         The Holy Bible

In the Bible, God speaks to man in a human way.Let us listen attentively to what God
wanted to tell us.

                                                                          Adapted from CCC 109]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[We hear about God
                   from others, especially our
                   parents, the priest and
                   teachers. We learn many

things about God.

      We can help others to know Jesus by telling them what we learn
and telling them to read the stories of Jesus from the Bible.

      Let us show love and respect to the Word of God when it is read
during Holy Mass. We have to listen attentively because it tells us about
the life of Jesus, his words and actions. He says many things and gives
us examples to lead us to His father.]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[Draw a Bible:                                 The Bible is a way of getting
                                       to know God. The Bible contains
                                       the Old Testament and the New
                                       Testament.

               God speaks to us in the Bible.]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[Everyday, we read the Word of
                                                       God from the Bible.

                                                           As we listen to the Word of
God, we think about the message God is giving us through the stories
of Jesus written in the Bible.

    Let us hold the Bible properly with respect. Help others how to use
the Bible or the Lectionary which contains the readings of each day.

Say this little prayer:

    O God, we thank you for giving us your written word and the story
                                                               about the life of Jesus.
                                                               Teach us to listen with love
                                                               and to do what you want.

Learn this Song: Listen….

    Listen with the ear of your heart and hear the voice of God, calling
    us to respond creatively and share the gifts we have.

    Living the message of the Gospel in our lives. We must strengthen
    one another in faith.]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[WE PROFESS OUR FAITH

                Let Us Get Together]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[WE PROFESS OUR FAITH

   This unit focuses on the Doctrinal Truths of our faith which include the
Blessed Trinity, the Human Person, the Church and the Blessed Virgin
Mary. The learners are introduced to learn about the basic doctrines of
the Apostles’ Creed. They are gradually led to belief, conviction and
commitment of their faith. They are also invited and challenged to
take an active role in the mission of the Church as baptized members.
The learners are presented a model of faith and virtues in the person of
the Blessed Virgin Mary.

                                                                        The Author

                              Marie Rivier, Woman of Faith]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[Lesson
             We

   Believe In

Expected
Outcomes:
a. To explain
why we call
God as Father.
b. To treat
others kindly
because we are
all children of
God.
c. To thank God
for giving us mind and body.

                 Look at the picture of the child and the father.
Teacher: What does a father do for his child? Pupil: He works, gives,
protects, loves, teaches us.]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[Teacher: Your father does not keep on saying that he loves you. He
              shows his love and care by the things he does.

Teacher: Tell us some of your experiences on how your father loves
              you.

Pupil: He sends us to school and provides for our needs at home.

Teacher: Let us think about God, our Father how He loves us. How does
              God show His love for us? What does God give us? How does
              God protect us? God always shows His love and care for us.
              He made everything with love for you and me. Do you know
              of someone except God who loves us?

Pupil: Our parents, brothers, sisters, our elders, friends and
              neighbors.

What are the things made by your father? What are the things made
by God, our Father? What is the difference between a maker and

                                                     being the

          Creator? Who can be a
          maker?Who can be the

Creator?]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[What did Jesus and His parents do in Jerusalem?
What happened to Jesus? Why did He remain behind in Jerusalem?

                                                     God is called Father as He is our
                                                     creator.
                                                     God has gifted us with body and
                                                     soul.
God blessed us with gifts of good eyes, ears, tongues, hands, and feet
in order to enjoy the other wonderful things made by Him.
God blessed us also with hearts and minds to think, to choose and
remember things. We have a soul to know and love God. We can
appreciate the things He gave us.

    By calling God “Father” we believe that everything comes from Him and HE
loves us as His children. He gives us His loving care. He gives us body and soul.

                                                                                   Adapted CCC 239; 362]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[There are so
                many things that
                people can do, but
                animals cannot do

them.

      For example a dog is different from a human person. A dog can
bark but he cannot come to school to learn. He cannot talk and
answer questions as we do.

      For human beings like us, we have the intellect to understand, we
can acquire new ideas, we can create new things and then change
them, and we have the feelings to be happy, to be afraid or to worry.
These are all beautiful gifts freely given by God that we can use

                                                          everyday.

                Everything we see comes from
                God. The more we learn about
                God, the more we praise, love

and serve Him.]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[Draw yourself.

    Let us try today to see how much we learn about God from others
and reach out also to others.

    God wants us to use our eyes and ears to learn from our parents,
priests and teachers.]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[We can touch the hearts of the needy
by sharing something from what we
have.

Say this prayer:

    O God, help me to use my eyes and
    my ears to learn about You. I want to
    love You and help others to love You,
    too.

    Thank you for being a loving Father to
    us as we are your loving children. Amen.]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[and approached the Prince. He needed the money for the
sustenance of his family. The Prince asked Inciong. “Why are you
here?” Inciong answered politely. “I want to stay with you and help
clean your beautiful garden. The Prince welcomed Inciong and
gave him work. He was in-
charge of taking care of plants and flowers and cleaning
the backyard. While Inciong was doing his work he found a treasure
under the stairway at the back of the storage house.

    The Prince did not know about it but Inciong brought the treasure to
the prince and told him that he found it. The Prince took the treasure
and gave it back to Inciong as he said, “You can have them, give it to
your family and the rest share it to your neighbors especially to the
poor. Inciong was a good man, hardworking, humble and honest. He
went home happily and thanked God for the generous prince.

What kind of a man was the Prince?

                                                             Do you want to know who

                                                         taught Inciong to be humble,

hardworking and honest man? What happens to us if we are not

honest or humble? What must we do to show kindness to Jesus and

others?]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[Jesus is the only Son of the Father who often teaches the people
about His Father in heaven. God the Father wants us to listen to Him

                                                         and obey Him.

                                                         We believe in Jesus as the Son
                                                         of God.

                                                                If we believe in
Jesus, we also believe in God, the Father, who sent Him.

      By faith we believe in Jesus Christ as we also express it when we
recite the Apostles’ Creed.

      We also know God and obey Him and worship Him when we
draw close to Jesus.

      When we believe in Jesus and obey Him, we have the Holy Spirit
in us.

      When we recite the Apostles’ Creed we pronounce our faith in
God.

      Through Jesus we can love and know more about God the Father.

    The title “Son of God” signifies the unique relationship of Jesus Christ to God his
Father: He is the only son of the Father, He is God himself. To be a Christian, one
must believe that Jesus Christ is the Son of God.

                                                                                            CCC 454]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[Jesus Christ is the model
                                                            of all Christians. Through
                                                            Jesus, we come to know
                                                            about his Father who is our
Father too. When Jesus taught us the prayer, “Our Father,” we are
happy to listen and obey him. Even though we have not seen God, but
we believe that He is present by seeing Jesus, His creations and the
people around us.

      Jesus always answers our prayers. He is our brother who is willing to
help us, love us, and care for all of us especially the poor and the
needy.

      Jesus is a friend to us. He never abandons us. We accept all what
He teaches us through the teachings of the Church.

      Jesus is the son of God. He is our brother. We have to believe in
                                                      the power of Jesus.

                                                             Say this always, “I believe
                                                      in God the Father Almighty,
Creator of heaven and earth. I believe in Jesus Christ, His only Son our
Lord and I believe in the Holy Spirit.”

Relate one story of Jesus with his Apostles.

      Make the sign of the Cross + properly. Then let us recite the
Doxology: “Glory be….”]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[We pray for the victims of
                                                       flood. That Jesus may help them
                                                       find shelter and send them
                                                       generous people to help them.

    Through the help of our parents or brothers and sisters, we also
gather used clothing and food of any kinds and give them to the
victims and the poor.

    We will also invite our neighbors to help the victims of calamities.

                                                               Let us pray:

                                                                        Jesus, the Son of
             God, please help those children
            who are in need of your support. We believe in your
            saving power. Please save those who are dying as
            you saved the apostles from the storm.]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[LessonWe Believe In

                                               Expected Outcomes:
                                               a. To realize that the Holy Spirit gives
                                               light, life and He loves us.
b. To ask help from the Holy Spirit as He is our consoler.

c. To pray to the Holy Spirit to increase our faith to believe in God.
                                    Be a Light to My Path

      Maribel, Maricel and Marilou are identical triplets whose family
name is Carciano. Their parents are in London earning money for the
family. The girls are staying together with their Lola. They manage to
prepare their things by themselves before they go to school everyday.
Their Lola takes good care of them, prepares food for their baon]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[everyday and guides them in whatever they do.]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[They are lovely little triplets who are now in grade two. It’s nice to
see them in their pink bags. They also have pink ribbons on their head
which look neat and clean.

      On Sundays they never missed the afternoon Holy Mass for
children. They are active members of the choir. During their first
communion, they also read the Word of God. Maribel read the First
Reading; Maricel read the Second Reading while Marilou sang the
Responsorial Psalms.

      They show good example to other children on how to be close to
God. They are three but one in spirit who give joy to the people around
them and learn to love God more than others.

   Do you know of other triplets? What is common to them? Aside from
their Lola, who teaches Maribel, Maricel and Marilou to be good girls?

This is the role of the Holy Spirit in our lives. He enlightens our minds
                                                     and guides us to the right
                                                     path.

                                      He also inspires us to do

good things and help others in need.

The Holy Spirit also guides us to become mature Christians.]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[Jesus sent His Holy Spirit to His apostles as a helper to teach them
everything. The Holy Spirit will help His apostles to proclaim the Good
News to every one and to let the Apostles remember what Jesus told
them. The Holy Spirit dwelt in their hearts. He made them strong to do
what God wanted them to do.

                                 We believe in the Holy
                           Spirit – that is the Spirit of
                           God who comes to us. We
                           welcome him in faith to

make our hearts His home.

      We believe that there is only one God but with three persons
called the Blessed Trinity.

      The Holy Spirit is one of the three persons. He is the third person in
the Blessed Trinity.

      We believe that after Jesus ascended into heaven he sent the
Holy Spirit to guide the Church until he comes again. The Holy Spirit is
the one at work among us now.

    To believe in the Holy Spirit is to profess that the Holy Spirit is one of the
persons of the Holy Trinity, with God the Father and God the Son, which we
worshipped and glorified.

                                                                          Adapted from CCC 685]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[Hence the Holy Spirit is a
                                                            special helper. We have
                                                            reasons to call on the Holy
                                                            Spirit for help when we are
afraid and when we have important things to do.

      If we want to be a good follower of Jesus, we must listen to the
Holy Spirit through the leaders of the church whom He has chosen like
our Pope, Bishops, Priests and Lay Ministers of the Church.

      We cannot see the Holy Spirit with our eyes but with our faith.
When we gather together in the name of Jesus, we can feel his
presence.

      The Holy Spirit came down upon the apostles to help them, guide
                                                      them and enlighten them what
                                                      to proclaim to the people of
                                                      God.

      The Holy Spirit is the Third Person in the Blessed Trinity.

Memorize the Prayer to the Holy Spirit:

      “Come Holy Spirit, fill the hearts of your faithful, and enkindle in
them the fire of your Word.”

    We usually invoke or call the Holy Spirit to be with us before we start
our prayer at home, in school or in a community.]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[We also ask the Holy Spirit to enlighten our minds, to help us
remember what we have studied and to help us to be honest during
examinations.

                                           Let us sing:

                                                            Come Holy Spirit I need you!
                               Come Holy Spirit I pray! Come with your strength
                               and your power! Come in your own gentle way.

                                                            (Repeat)

Let us pray:
Dear Holy Spirit, come and make me grow in your love. Teach me how
to love others and how to become like Jesus. Amen.]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[LessonWe Believe That

                                               Expected Outcomes:
                                               a. To define Church as people of
                                               Gods’ family.
                                               b. To show love and care to the
members of the Church.
c. To pray for the leaders and fellow members of the Church.

                                        A Happy Family
      Mang Kedo and Aling Anita have ten children. They lived in a
barrio of Lugpay, two kilometers away from the poblacion. Some of
their children went to school from Monday to Friday. The younger
ones stayed at home and helped their parents.

      Every Saturday evening Aling, Anita gathered the members of
the family to pray the rosary followed by the reading from the Bible.

      Mang Kedo was a kind and good story teller. The children used to
listen to their father telling stories about God. Everyone in the family
listened attentively to the stories of Jesus in the Gospels. Through this
way, they will always remember how much God loves them. They
believed that stories tell many things. Stories can teach us about the
world and about many things that happened long time ago. Stories
can teach us good values that we can share to others.]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[Abov
e all Mang
Kedo and
Aling Anita
taught
their
children
how to live
the lifestyle
of Jesus, as
they
belong to
God’s
family in
their GKK.
They
always
remember
to go to
their Parish
Church to
attend the
Holy Mass
on
Sundays
and Holy
days of
obligations
.]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[Where do you hear about the
                  stories from the Bible? How can
                  the stories from the Bible teach

you about Jesus?

Draw your family going to your Parish church. Write 1
sentence story below your drawing.

                  We are the members of the Church.]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[Jesus wanted us to unite with him. We should belong to him. So he
built his Church and gathered his people to follow him. He chose Peter
to be his successor as leader of the Church.]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[What did Jesus and His parents do in Jerusalem? What happened to
Jesus? Why did He remain behind in Jerusalem?

                                                     We believe in the One, Holy
                                                     Catholic Apostolic Church. This
                                                     means that we belong to God’s
Family. The Church is the people of God. It is also where the people

gathered together to worship God. The community of Jesus’
followers is called the Church. The community of believers is of one
heart and one mind.

         Our parish is a community where people share their
  faith together at Holy Mass. If we are members of the
  Church, we belong to the community of Jesus.

      In the first community of Jesus, he chose twelve Apostles
to lead his flock.

      Today, the Pope, the Bishops and the Priests continue the work of
the Apostles. They are the leaders of the Church and we are the
members.

    Christ “is the head of the Body, the Church.” We are the members of His
Body, the Church. “Christ loved the Church and gave himself up for her, that he
might sanctify her.”

                                                                             Adapted from CCC 792, 796]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[Wherever we are, we
                            remain members of the
                            Christian community
                            because we follow the

teachings of Jesus Christ.

      God wants us to be active in sharing our faith, hope and love
among ourselves at home, in school or in the parish where we
belong.

      We have to be good to our neighbors because they are also
members of the church. Let us share what we have to them especially
to the poor.

      Our own family is a small church or community where we learn to
help one another and love our parents, brothers and sisters.

      The Church would also mean a building where all the members
gather together to worship God.

                                                                 We express our faith
                                                          when we recite the
                                                          Apostles’ Creed.
      “We believe in God, the Father Almighty…Creator of Heaven
and Earth.
      We believe in Jesus Christ, His only Son our Lord. Who was
conceived by the Holy Spirit born of the Virgin Mary. We believe in the
Holy Spirit and the Holy Catholic Church. Memorize the prayer, the
“Apostles Creed.”]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[As members of the Church we
                                                   must do the following:

                                                        At home – we help clean the
                                surroundings, wash dishes,
and water the plants.

           In school – we clean our classroom, arrange the chairs
and tables.

           In our neighborhood – we share some food or clothing
especially to the poor.

                                                            Let us pray:]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[Lesson         The  Mother  Of  God
        Mary,

Expected Outcomes:
                                                   a. To identify the important role of
                                                   Mary as the Mother of the Church
                                                   and as our mother, too.
                                                   b. To show efforts in putting into

practice the virtues of Mary.
c. To offer our prayers in honor of Mary.

      We love our mother. She is a very good housekeeper. She stays
at home while our father goes to work to earn money for our family.

      Our mother takes good care of us. She cooks food and prepares
everything for us.

      When we arrive home from school the table is ready and delicious
food is served. All of us in the family are happy to praise and thank God
for having a responsible and humble mother. We are close to her. She
helps us in all our needs. She loves all of us.

      We make her happy especially on her birthday and during
mother’s day. We invite her to school when we celebrate parents’
day, too. We prepare dances and sing melodious songs on some
memorable days. What a surprise for her when we give her bouquet of
flowers, simple gifts, and nice cards with loving notes! The celebration is
simple but meaningful. We learn to love our mother as God loves her.]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[How do you make your own
                                                     mother happy? How does your
mother take good care of you? Why do we show love and respect to
our mother? How wonderful it is to have a loving mother but how do
we

give honor to the Mother of all mothers?]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[Mary was chosen by God the Father to be the Mother of Jesus.
She was the most blessed among all women.

      She believed and trusted God by obeying the words of the angel
coming from the Father.]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[Mary was a woman of
                                                     great faith. She said YES to God
                                                     and accepted to be the Mother
                                                     of Jesus. She is the most favored
one of all women in the world. She is always ready to assists us when
we ask for her help.
      It is important on our part as Catholic to increase our devotion to
Mother Mary because she is our Mother too. Her virtues will help us
grow spiritually.
      We honor Mary as the Mother of God, Mother of all mankind,
Queen of heaven and earth, Lady of all nations, Queen of the Holy
Rosary, Immaculate Conception and Patroness of our country,
Philippines.

      Mary has many titles as it is stated in the litany of the Blessed
Virgin Mary. We pray and give homage to Mary everyday
especially on her special days and feast days.

At the announcement that Mary would give birth to “the Son of the Most High” Mary
responded with the obedience of faith that with God nothing is impossible. Let it be
done to me according to your word, with Mary’s YES, she becomes the Mother of Jesus.

                                                                          Adapted from CCC 494]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[When we recite the
                                                               prayer: Holy Mary,
                                                               Mother of God pray for
us sinners now and at the hour of our death, we invoke the help of
Mary to protect us in times of disasters; flood, fire, earthquake,
typhoons and even during war.

      Praying of the Holy Rosary at home, in school and in the Church is
very important. Praying to Mary will strengthen our faith. Mary, as
Mother of the Church will always intercede for all our intentions.

      In her feast days, we remember her through songs and
prayers. We even offer flowers and light the candles to show
that we love her. She loves us, too as she loves Jesus.

Like Mary we must be obedient, kind, humble, simple, modest,
                                                   industrious, honest, generous,
                                                   courageous and prayerful.

                       Memorize the following

prayers

Our Father -Hail Mary - Glory Be Apostles’ Creed -Hail Holy

Queen

         -O My Jesus.

Find a corner in your home and make an altar where you can place
the Statue of Mary or big picture of Mary. Decorate it with beautiful

                                                       flowers and put candles around
                                                       it.]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[Invite your family: Mother – Father – Brother, Sisters and
                                                    elders to pray together

                                                  before going to bed in the
                                                               evening.

                                                      Let us pray together:

               Hail Mary Hail Holy Queen]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[Let us sing: life resemble more your own each
                  day.//

Bless O
Mother Mary

Bless your
loving child
From your
hands so
gentle
Pure and
undefiled
Bless all
that I ever
think or do
or say
//That my]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[Lesson

                                                   Expected Outcomes:
                                                   a. To recognize Mary’s role as the
                                                   Mother of the world.
b. To express how to honor Mary, our Mother.

c. To pray the Marian prayer faithfully especially the rosary.
                                   A Short Story of Jonas

             Jonas was born as the only child. His parents went to
another country to find a job and earn money for his future.
He was only three years old when his parents left him to his
grandmother, Nanay Estrella. He was well taken cared of by his
grandmother.]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[Few years later, Jonas started his schooling in their barrio where
the school is near their house. Every time they had parents’ meeting,
Nanay Estrella always attend representing the parents of Jonas.
Many times Jonas was given awards in school.

      Nanay Estrella, his Lola became the second parent of Jonas. He
learned to love his grandmother while his parents were working hard
for him. After a year his parents came back for a visit and to be with
Jonas for a while.

                                                         Who took good
                                                      care of Jonas
                                                      when his parents
went to another country? How did Jonas feel especially
when he received awards in school? What was the role
of Nanay Estrella in the life of Jonas? What happens if
nobody will take good care of us? Does a mother play
an important role in our life?Why? Do you want to know
also about the role of Mary, the Mother of Jesus, in our
life?

   When God sent Jesus to be our Savior, He chose Mary to be the
Mother of Jesus and our Mother, too. Mary is our model in faith.]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[The Virgin Mary is acknowledged and honored as being truly the
Mother of God and of the redeemer. Mary’s role in the church cannot
be separated from her union with Christ. This union of the mother with
the Son was known from the time when Jesus was conceived till the
hour of his death.]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[When did Mary become the Mother of Mankind? We believe that
Mary is the Mother of God, but she became our Mother.

              Blessed Virgin Mary was
        chosen by God as the Mother of
        Jesus and our mother, too. We
        honor Mary through prayers and

songs.

a. Hail Mary full of grace, the Lord is with you. Blessed
    are you among women, and blessed is the fruit of you
    womb, Jesus. Holy Mary, Mother of God, pray for us
    sinners, now and at the hour of our death. Amen.

b. Hail Holy Queen, Mother of Mercy, hail our Life, our
    sweetness and our hope, to you do we cry, poor
    banished children of Eve, to you do we send up our
    sighs, mourning and weeping this vale of tears. Turn
    then most gracious advocate, your mercy toward us,
    and after this our exile, show unto us the blessed fruit of
    your womb, Jesus. O Clement, O Loving, O Sweet Virgin
    Mary.

c. Remember O most gracious Virgin Mary that never
    was it known, that anyone who fled to your protection,
    implored you help, or sought your intercession was left
    unaided. Inspired with this confidence, I fly unto you
    O Virgin of Virgins my Mother, to you I come; before
    you I stand sinful and sorrowful. O mother of the Word
    incarnate despise not my petition but in your mercy
    hear and answer me. Amen.]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[We believe that the Holy Mother of God became the Mother of the Church and
continues in heaven to do her maternal role on behalf of the members of Christ.

                                                                          Adapted from CCC 975

      Mary helps us and loves us. She keeps us close to Jesus. She is like
our real mother who is ready to protect us. With Jesus, we must love

                                                               Mary by praying to her
                                                               often. We always
                                                               remember her everyday
especially on her feast days. There are times when we join the
procession in thanksgiving for taking care of us during calamities. We
recite the Holy Rosary at home together with our family and in school
with our teachers and schoolmates.]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[We believe in truth that
                                                      Mary is the Mother of the Son of
                                                      God. If Jesus is the King of the
universe, Mary is the Queen of all queens on earth.

      Memorize the prayer in honor of Mary as queen of heaven and

earth. Pray the Hail Holy Queen……… Pray the Angelus………………….

Pray the Rosary…………………..

We remember Mary on September 8-her Birthday.

    We commemorate her feast days on December 8, her Immaculate
Conception and on January 1, her Motherhood. August 15, is the feast

                                                   day Our Lady of the Assumption.

                                    We stop walking when
                                we hear the bell rings for the

Angelus.

We must pray to Mary everyday.

    We must learn to follow her examples being humble and
obedient.

We must show our love to Mary the way we love our own mother.]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[Let us sing together the
                                                                        songs to Mary:

                                                                                            Bless,
O Mother Mary, Bless your loving child. With your hands so gentle, Pure
and
undefiled.
Bless all that I ever think or do or say. //That my life resembles more
thine own each day.//

We offer flowers to Mary while singing:

                                     Mary is Our Queen
Mary is our queen, O sing to her Mary is our Mother, trust in her Mary is

        the star that shines at night Guiding us to Jesus our true light
                            Mary is the creature of our race

                        Whom the Holy Spirit filled with grace
     To become the Mother of our Lord The God whom she adores.

                    Ave, Ave, Ave Maria Ave, Ave, Ave Maria
                               (repeat: Mary is our Queen)]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[Immaculate Mother

                    Immaculate Mother We come at thy call
                    And low at thy altar, before thee we call,

                Ref. Ave, Ave, Ave Maria. Ave, Ave, Ave Maria.

 We pray for our Mother The Church upon earth And bless Sweetest
                           Lady, the land of our birth (Ref.)

In grief and temptation, in joy and in pain. We’ll seek thee our Mother
                               Nor seek thee in vain (Ref).]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[WE LIVE OUR FAITH

   This unit focuses on the Moral Truths of our faith which include Man’s
Vocation, Ten Commandments, Persons and Society. The learners are
led to recognize, discern and commit to one’s vocation in life. They
are expected to know, interiorize and integrate the commandments
in their lives. They are challenged to engage in service and to exercise
responsible stewardship to the various communities to which they
belong: family, school, parish, civic and global.

                                                                        The Author

                               Marie Rivier, Woman of Zeal]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[Lesson

Expected
Outcomes:
a. To realize
that we are
called to
proclaim
God’s
Kingdom.
b. To do things
pleasing to God and to others.
c. To pray for those who are in need of our help.

                                Telling Others About Jesus

      Bethsaida is the eldest daughter of Mr. and Mrs. Cruz. They belong
to San Isidro GKK. Every Saturday afternoon, Bethsaida spends her little
time in selling a magazine called “The Torch”. Her parents allowed her
to do such job not only to help earn a living for the family but to tell
others about God in proclaiming the Good News to the people in the
community.]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[Bethsaida was only in Grade Two when she started working in their
GKK. Her father and mother were proud of her because she read and
explained the content of the article in the newsletter that she was
selling. She will just find a corner down the street, then many men and
women, poor and rich, young and old alike went near her and listened
to her stories. A small little girl, lovely and simple was happy doing what
God wants. She believed that her effort is God’s love at work in her.

What did Bethsaida do before the people will buy her magazine? What
                                                      is the most important thing that
                                                      happened in her life? What does
                                                      Jesus want us to do in His

Kingdom? How can you make others learn about Jesus?]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[Jesus has a special love for children. He is always with us. What did
Jesus tell his disciples when he saw them sending
the children away? What should you do to be blessed by Jesus as what
he did to the little children?

      God’s Kingdom is here on earth as in heaven. We proclaim the
                                                         Kingdom of God when we do
                                                         even the smallest thing. When
                                                         we say, “Your Kingdom come,

Your will be done on earth as in Heaven,” we do what God wants. We
want to reach heaven where we experience lasting happiness with
God, Jesus, Mary and all the saints and angels. We look for ways on
how to follow Jesus’ examples. When we do good things, when we are
kind and polite to others and when we think of something good for us
and for others, we proclaim the Kingdom of God anytime,

    By prayer we can discern “what is the will of God” and obtain the endurance
    to do it. Jesus teaches us that one enters the Kingdom of God not only by
    speaking but by doing the will of my Father in heaven.

                                                                                                     CCC 282]]></page><page Index="93"><![CDATA[Many times we follow the
                                                            people who can bring us to
                                                            heaven. But we have to see
                                                            if we are worthy to follow
those who lead us. It is also our responsibility to make others happy and
lead them to heaven. Whether we are young or old the Kingdom of
God is for all. We make effort to be kind, generous, helpful, obedient,
compassionate, friendly, humble and loving to our parents and elders,
friends and neighbors, teachers and leaders of our community. This is
the way to realize the Kingdom of God in our midst. Let us learn to be
patient because sometimes we meet difficulties in proclaiming in
God’s Kingdom.

      Jesus teaches us to follow his teachings through his stories in the
                                                      Bible.
                                                             Relate one story of Jesus
                                                      which shows how to help others
                                                      in times of needs.

“The Multiplication of the Loaves” “Jesus Feed Five Thousand People”

Prepare some old clothes that you can give to the poor.

    Help in the distribution of food to children who are neglected by
their parents.]]></page><page Index="94"><![CDATA[Volunteer to contribute some amount to buy medicine for the
evacuees.

Learn this song:

    Seek ye first the Kingdom of God and His righteousness
    and all these things shall be added unto you, Allelu… Alleluia
    Alleluia…..4x]]></page><page Index="95"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="96"><![CDATA[Others enjoy shopping, visiting their farms or have a gathering with
their relatives. Some families go to see good movies or other sorts of
enjoyment.

      While some families enjoy their weekends at home, the family of
Mang Endo prefers to gather together in their GKK, the community
where they belong. They never miss to celebrate mass, to adore and
worship God on Sundays even Holydays. They believe that Holy Mass
is the greatest act of prayer that they can offer to God.

                                                         Tell something about the family
                                                         of Mang Endo. How do they
enjoy their weekends? What about the other families? How about your
own family? Where do you spend your weekends? What does God
want us to do for Him especially on

Sundays? What is the best offering we can give to God? How do
we worship God? What happens if we do not go to Mass at all?]]></page><page Index="97"><![CDATA[Jesus summed up the Ten Commandments into two great
commandments which is love of God and love of neighbor.]]></page><page Index="98"><![CDATA[Jesus summed up the
                                                         Ten Commandments in two
                                                         greatest commandments, a)
                                                         You shall love the Lord your
God with all your heart, and with all your soul, and with all your mind,
and b) You shall love your neighbor as yourself.
      To adore God is to acknowledge him as God, creator and
savior, the Lord and Master of everything that we see.
      The Lord’s name is holy. We should not abuse it. We must keep
the name of the Lord in mind and in silent loving adoration.
      We invoke the name of God when we begin our prayer with the
Sign of the Cross as we say: “In the name of the Father and of the Son,
and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.
      The Lord’s Day is the day which the Lord has made; let us rejoice
and be glad in it. It is Sunday. We all gather on his day, the first day
when God made the world and also the day Jesus Christ, our Savior
rose from the dead.

The Ten Commandments state what is required in the love of God and love of
neighbor. The first three concern love of God and the other seven love of neighbor….

                                                                                          CCC 2067]]></page><page Index="99"><![CDATA[God loves us. Jesus loves us.
                                                            We love God, too.

                                                                   We have the duty to
worship Him above all things. Sometimes we forget to pray every
day. But as children of God we must adore and worship God through
our prayers, when we visit God in the Church, and above all when
we celebrate the Holy Sacrifice of the Mass on Sundays and special
days in the Church, the house of prayer.

      We must come together in praying for one another and express
our unity and love to God by praying or singing the Lord’s Prayer.

      We are close to Jesus especially when we receive Holy
Communion every time we attend Mass.

Jesus told us to follow the commandments of love. What are the two
greatest commandments of God? Enumerate the 10 COMANDMENTS

                                                      of God.

Show in your drawing that you follow the rules of God. At home:]]></page><page Index="100"><![CDATA[In school:

                                          In the community:

                                                   Let us sing together this song:

“Father, I adore You, Lay my life before You. How I love
You. Jesus, I adore You, Lay my life before You. How I love
You. Spirit, I adore You, Lay my life before You. How I love
you Mary, I implore you. Lay my life before you. How I love
you. Marie Rivier, I implore you. Lay my life before you.
How I love you.]]></page><page Index="101"><![CDATA[Lesson

        Expected Outcomes:
        a. To realize that we love God when
        we love others even our enemies.
        b. To show act of kindness and

forgiveness to those we hurt.
c. To pray for the grace to love one another.

                                  Showing Love to Others

Pepito and Carolino were best friends. One day, when Carolino was
      pasturing his carabao in

their farm, he saw a group of three boys bringing some fish.]]></page><page Index="102"><![CDATA[He did not know that the tilapia in their fishpond was harvested
by their care taker and he sold everything to people around them.

      Carolino went home and told his father about what happened to
their fishpond. But the father of Carolino cannot go to their fishpond
because he could hardly walk. So Carolino went to his nearest
neighbor and told Pepito to help him. Pepito was really a good friend
of him. He just told Carolino to be patient until they will hear from the
care taker. The care taker told them that he gave some fish to the
three boys because they helped him harvest the tilapia. The boys were
from a poor family and those fish were very

timely for their lunch. So Carolino and Pepito advised those boys to
      bring the

fish to their parents to be cooked for their lunch.
      Carolino learned to be kind and generous to others especially

to the needy. They followed what they learned that everyone must
                                                         love even their enemies.

                                                         What part of the story do you
                                                         like most? How did the care
taker show kindness to the three boys? Who are those persons you
love? Which person do you find easiest to love?Why? Which person do
you find difficult to love?Why? What do you think will happen if we all
loved one another? How can you show to Jesus that you love him?]]></page><page Index="103"><![CDATA[Jesus reminds us to always love one another because he loves us
too. To love means you are ready to forgive and show respect to

                                                      everyone even to your enemies.

                                                            Jesus said to his disciples:
                                                      “Love one another even as I
                                                      have loved you.”
      The New Commandment of Jesus to “love one

another” is part of the final instructions given to his disciples
after the Last Supper had “ended”, and after Judas Iscariot had
departed.]]></page><page Index="104"><![CDATA[“Love one another,” means loving all regardless of race color and
language because they also belonged to Christ.

      Jesus reminds us that when we love, we love all even our
enemies, even those who are far away from us. Loving one another is
to be ready to be hurt and to forgive and forget the bad things that
had happened.

    Christ died out of love for us, while we were still “enemies.” The Lord asks us to
love as He does, even our enemies, to make ourselves the neighbor of those farthest
away, and to love children and the poor as Christ himself.

                                                                                          CCC 1825

                                                                      God is our loving
                                                               Father who wants us to
                                                               love one another. He is
never tired of loving us. Loving others is one way of loving God. We
need one another but sometimes we also hurt one another. But like
God, we should also never get tired of loving those who have hurt us.
When we hurt others we also hurt God.

      When we hurt others, we should ask for forgiveness. We also ask
God to forgive us as He never gets tired of forgiving us. When we love,
we are also ready to forgive. God wants us to live happily with one
another so, love, forgive and be a friend to one another and above all
pray for one another.]]></page><page Index="105"><![CDATA[Love your neighbor as yourself.
                                   Love your enemies. Memorize in
                                   your own words the Ten

Commandments.

1. Adore God 6. _________________

2. ______________ 7. _________________

3. ______________ 8. _________________

4. ______________ 9. _________________

5. ______________ 10. _________________

I will obey my parents when I’ll be asked to do the errands. I will respect
the things of my brothers and sisters at home. If I found the things that

                                                   belong to my classmates, I will
                                                   return them.]]></page><page Index="106"><![CDATA[Let us pray the:
                                                                         “Our Father”

                              Let us learn this song:

                              “Love One Another”

                                                                                //And care for
                                                                                each other// as
                                                                                I have cared for
                                                                                you. Forgive
                                                                                each other
here as I’ve forgiven you. Be friend to each one here as I’ve been
friend to you. (repeat: Love one another…)

                                                                    My dear children,
                                                                           We must praise the

                                                                    Lord every time we
                                                                    practice humility to
                                                                    know our failures. If we
love God through others, we must be humble and love those who hate
us.]]></page><page Index="107"><![CDATA[Lesson

Expected Outcomes:             a. To tell how to live as true Christians
God’s call by helping others.  in whatever state of life we are in.
                               b. To demonstrate how to respond to

c. To pray for people who help us.

                                     Victims of Typhoons

      The Barangay Captain announced to the people living in
Barangay Lepags that many evacuees are coming to stay in the gym
because they lost their houses and]]></page><page Index="108"><![CDATA[belongings during the big flood in their place. They need
food and shelter in order to survive. Before the evacuees arrived
the generous people of God in Lepags prepared what to give to
the victims.

      Many children, youth and community helpers volunteered to
distribute the relief goods such as food, clothing, rice and all kinds of
canned goods. The medical team came and distributed medicines
to those who were sick while the doctors and nurses took good care
of the health of the victims.

      The nearby schools in Lepags organized some pupils to collect
milk and bread for the children and the grade 2 class of Ms. Doris went
out of their classroom to distribute what they have to the victims. Their
teachers were happy to see the pupils helping one another in taking
care of the victims of flood. They lived the love of Jesus for the poor
and the needy.

   Everywhere around us we see many people who need our help.
                                                         Sometimes many victims of
                                                         calamities will come to us and
                                                         ask for help.

   What should we do with these people? How do you feel when you
see these people sleeping along the road without mat or blankets?

   Do you want to learn more from the story of Jesus on how to show
love and compassion to the needy?]]></page><page Index="109"><![CDATA[Which of these three in your opinion was a neighbor to the victim?

    The Good Samaritan gave us the true example of a loving service
to others. When we do good to others we proclaim the teaching of
Jesus on how to show love and care to our brothers and sisters who
need our help.]]></page><page Index="110"><![CDATA[We are created by God to
                                                         love Him. We also learn to love
                                                         others because God loves us.

      Jesus teaches us how to love people around us. We are called to
show concern to those who are suffering especially the poor and the
needy.

    The duty of making oneself a neighbor to others and actively serving them
become even more urgent when it involves the disadvantaged, in whatever area this
may be….

                                                                                          CCC 1932

                                                                      We are from
                                                               different families but we
                                                               belong to God’s family.

                                                                      People, no matter in
what state of life they are in, learn to work and help one another as
true Christians.

      Sometimes, we have to think of the needs of others and make
them happy.]]></page><page Index="111"><![CDATA[We need others to help us and we have to work with others and
help them so that everything will be done out of love.

If we can live with others, Jesus himself will live within us.

                      Live the way God wants you to
                      live in a Christian way. Relate the
                      story of the Good Samaritan.

Dramatize the story.

Our mother cooks food for us. We help her wash the dishes after lunch
                                                   or supper. We clean the table after
                                                   eating. When we help, we do not
                                                   expect a reward. It must be done

sincerely and with love.]]></page><page Index="112"><![CDATA[Let us sing together this
                                                               song:

                                                               Refrain:
                                            Whatsoever you do to the least of my
                                            brothers that you do unto to me.

                                            ( Repeat 3 times )

                                                          Let us pray together:

                                            Dear Jesus, Help us to bring peace, love
and joy to others. Give us the grace to visit those who are sad and

                              lonely. Guide us to show love and concern to the
                              poor and the needy.]]></page><page Index="113"><![CDATA[Lesson

Expected Outcomes:

                    a. To realize that Jesus teaches us
                    how to love and serve others.
                    b. To show to others that we serve

and care for them.
c. To pray that we will become true friends of Jesus as we serve others.

                                                            pls. provide title

      We are happy to be in school everyday. We live by what we see
and learn. Ms. Beda is our grade two adviser. She teaches many
beautiful things to help us grow in God’s love every day.

      One morning, we noticed that she was sad. After she checked the
attendance, she announced that Zeny one of our classmates was
absent again. She was already absent for a couple of days. We were
worried too because we don’t want to miss the presence of our]]></page><page Index="114"><![CDATA[classmate.]]></page><page Index="115"><![CDATA[During noon break we went to visit Zeny in their house. She got
sick. Her mother was taking care of her. Zeny cannot eat well.

      In the afternoon we told Ms. Beda that Zeny got sick and she
cannot eat hard food. So, our teacher told the grade 2 class what to
bring for Zeny. Some of us brought milk, eggs and bread for her
breakfast and others brought fruits for her. Her mother was so grateful
for the help we offered to Zeny. When she got well, all of us said,” thank
you God for bringing back the good health of Zeny. Thank you too,
that we were also able to give our love and care to Zeny.”

What did you learn from the story of Zeny? What did Ms Beda teach her

grade two pupils? What happened to her pupil, Zeny? What did some

pupils bring for Zeny? How do you care and love others who are sick?

                                                         What virtues do you practice in

                                                         order to serve others?

   Jesus teaches us that when we help those in need we do the deed
for him. Jesus tells us that whatever we do to others we do it for him.]]></page><page Index="116"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="117"><![CDATA[Jesus helps us to live day by day to grow in God’s love. He teaches us
to love and serve others through his examples. He is our model of living

                                                                 the virtue of humility.

                                                                God created us to know
                                                         Him, to love Him, to serve Him
and to be happy with Him someday in heaven.
      If a man serves Christ, he is a good follower and true Christian. We
are made for service to care for our brothers and sisters. We are made
to share our joy to one another.
      We must give time to listen and talk about Jesus to the people
around us.]]></page><page Index="118"><![CDATA[Jesus shares the life of the poor from his birth to the cross because he experienced
hunger, thirst and neglected. He was sent by His Father to preach the good news to the
poor.

                                                                          Adapted from CCC 544

                                                                There are many ways of
                                                                       serving others:

     - We help our parents clean our garden. After doing their
        assignments, our elder brothers and sisters helped to
        clean the backyard. I water the plants every day.

     - Our classmates in school are busy cutting letters for our
        classroom reading corner. I volunteered to pick up
        pieces of paper and put them into the trash can.

     - A group of Altar Servers helped clean the church. I
        asked help from my friends to arrange flowers for the
        altar.

     - We were invited to attend the birthday party of our
        neighbor. Many visitors came with their friends. My
        mother was happy when she saw me welcoming the
        people.

     - It is not easy but when it is done with love then we are
        serving God through the people who need most of our
        service.]]></page><page Index="119"><![CDATA[A. Illustrate in your drawing that
                                                          your mother takes care of you when
                                                          you get sick.

B. Illustrate how you give your service to the people in the house of God, a place for
worship,
the church.]]></page><page Index="120"><![CDATA[When we go to church during Mass
                                                   we greet one another with a sign of
                                                   peace. This shows that we are brothers
                                                   and sisters who love, care and serves one
                                                   another.

    When we are at home we serve our parents by putting
things in their proper place every time we finish eating at table.

                                                                  Let us pray together:

                                                              Lord, make me a servant
                                                           with humble heart that I can
                                                           serve others especially to
                                                           those who are weak and
                           lonely, this we ask through Christ, our Lord, Amen.

                                                  Let us sing together:

                           We are made for service to care for all men.
                           We are made for love to each brother and sister.]]></page><page Index="121"><![CDATA[A love that will last through sorrow and pain.

A love that will never die with strain. Life can be so lonely, when
nobody cares. Life can be so lonely, when nobody shares. //But if man
gives himself to help other man, the happiness of Christ will live with
in.//]]></page><page Index="122"><![CDATA[Lesson

        Expected Outcomes:
        a. To realize that Jesus wants us to
        follow him in our daily life.
        b. To show example on how to

become followers of Jesus.
c. To pray for all people on earth especially those who do not know,
love and follow Jesus Christ.

                                       Follow and Obey

      What do you want to be in a few years? Do you want to be a
scout?Do you know who scouts are? Who are they? In Scouting, there is
always a scout leader and the rest are followers. As scouts, you have to
learn to follow and obey instructions for the success of your activities.]]></page><page Index="123"><![CDATA[The things that the scouts learn and do, prepare them to be
better grown up citizens of our country.

      This is also true to us who are followers of Jesus Christ. Jesus Christ
leaves leaders for us to follow. At home, we have our parents and
elders who direct us to the right way. In school, we have our teachers
who teach us many good things for our future. In the Church, we have
priests who direct us to Jesus Christ who is our highest leader.

      Therefore, our parents, teachers and priests represent Jesus Christ
here on earth. It is our responsibility to follow them because they are
our bridge to know, love and serve Jesus Christ. By obeying them, we
also obey Jesus Christ. Like the scout leader who always directs his
members to the right way, they also will lead us to heaven.

      Can you show now how to follow Jesus by following your
leader?

Let’s have a game……… “Follow the leader”

      The leader will stay at the center and say, “Do this, Do that,” and
everybody will follow. A leader must lead the group. So everybody will
follow wherever the leader will go.

If you can hear the voice of your leader, you will also hear the voice of
                                                         Jesus, our highest leader in the
                                                                          Church.]]></page><page Index="124"><![CDATA[The sheep in the pasture know their shepherd’s voice and footstep.
Even without looking, they can follow the voice of the shepherd as he
leads and walks along with them.]]></page><page Index="125"><![CDATA[Christ refers to himself as the Good Shepherd and to us
                                             as the flock.

                                         The sheep know the voice
                                   of their master as soon as he
                                   comes to the door of the

sheepfold.

      They listen to his voice, and when he calls their names, they follow
behind him. They know he loves and takes care of them.

      As a shepherd, he finds suitable food and sufficient drink for his
flock. He is always on the alert, ready to protect them from wild beast,
from thieves, and robbers. He even knows the name of each one of his
sheep.

      The sheep follow the shepherd who is their leader, and
are confident he will never desert them. They trust him and
they know he is strong enough to protect them.

      Jesus said that a good shepherd would even give his life to save
his sheep.

      Just as the sheep listen to the voice of the shepherd, let us also
listen to Jesus speaking in persons and events. Let us listen to him in the
Gospel as He said, “I am the Good Shepherd. I know my Sheep and my
Sheep know me…. For these sheep I will give My Life.”

Learn the following poem about the Good Shepherd.

• Good sheep love their shepherd
    He cares for all their needs,
    We love our shepherd, Jesus,
    And follow where He leads.]]></page><page Index="126"><![CDATA[• He knows and loves each one of us,
    And for our Sins He died, Oh, let us be His chosen lamb Forever at His
    side.

                                                                   Jesus is the Good
                                                            Shepherd and we are his
                                                            flock. As Good Shepherd,
                                                            Jesus gives his life for the
sheep. He is also the door of the sheep. Anyone who enters and go in
and out through him will be saved. He will find pasture for each one.
This means that Jesus opens the way to God. He came to tell men and
to show men what God was like, and he opened the door for men to
God.

      Jesus is the way; the way of peace, love and life. And his way, if
we will only take it, leads us closer and closer to God. The only way
that leads us to God in heaven is the way of love.

      To be a follower of Jesus, we follow how Jesus lived here on
earth.

      There were times that we failed to follow him because we do not
listen to his voice; we lack faith on him. Sometimes we find it difficult to
follow Christ’s teachings and example like: loving our neighbor
especially those who have hurt us. We also find it hard to go to Mass
every Sunday, to pray every night instead of looking at TV late in the
evening. Sometimes, like the sheep, we also get lost by refusing to
follow Christ and doing what we want. It is only in following Jesus’
teachings that would surely lead us to the right path.]]></page><page Index="127"><![CDATA[Are we ready to reach out to those who do not know Christ?To
bring peace to those who quarrel? To bring love to those who hate?
We can be the voice of Jesus Christ and act as the Good Shepherd for

                                                          others.

                                                          Who is our Good
                                                          Shepherd?What did he say?

                                                                Jesus said that a good
shepherd would even give his life to save his sheep. Let us learn the
poem about the Good Shepherd.

“I know My Sheep and My Sheep Know Me”

1 Good sheep love their shepherd. He cares for all their needs, We
love our Shepherd, Jesus. And follow where He leads.

2 He knows and love each one of us, And for our sins He died. Oh,
let us be His chosen Lambs, Forever at His side.

    We will go to the church and tell Jesus that we will always listen and
follow Him by obeying our parents at home: when they request us to
prepare food and drinks for our visitors or to take care of our pet dogs
and cats.]]></page><page Index="128"><![CDATA[Let us sing together:

                                                                                         The Lord
is my shepherd, He is Lord and I am his guest. Fresh and green are the
pastures where he leads me to my rest.
Near peaceful waters he leads me. To cheer up my cheerless heart. He
guides me on the safe path. He will always do his part.

Let us pray:
“O Jesus, our Good shepherd, teach us to follow you by keeping your

                                             commandments faithfully.”]]></page><page Index="129"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="130"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="131"><![CDATA[Lesson

Expected Outcomes:
a. To believe that the Father, Son and Holy Spirit dwell upon us at
baptism.
b. To show gratitude to God as members of Christian community.
c. To pray and thank God for calling us His children.

      One Sunday morning, the parents of Adrian brought the baby girl
to the church together with the godparents. The baby girl was
baptized by their Parish Priest and they named her Joan. Everyone in
the family rejoiced upon knowing that Joan received the sacrament of
baptism. She is now a member of the Church and a child of God.
Parents and godparents made the promises for Joan to become a
true Christian and good follower of Jesus Christ.]]></page><page Index="132"><![CDATA[1. Why did Adrian want to call
                                                     her Sister Joan?
                                                     2. Why did the parents of
   Adrian bring the baby to the Church?
3. What happened to the baby after she was baptized?
4. What are you going to tell those who were not yet baptized?
5. Do you want to know what happened to Jesus after he was
   baptized?]]></page><page Index="133"><![CDATA[At first, John cannot accept that he will baptize Jesus. But Jesus told
John that they only follow what God wants. This is an event when Jesus
was proclaimed as the Son of God.

                                                         Baptism is the first sacrament of
                                                                 initiation. It gives our

                                                         soul the new life of sanctifying
                                                         grace, by which we become
children of God and heirs of heaven. We become new members of
the Church. We live in God’s life and we grow in His great love as we
do our best in doing all things for Him.

             As baptized persons, we have to live the promises of
our parents and godparents. Let us also fulfill our duties as
followers of Jesus since we bear the name of Christ in new life.]]></page><page Index="134"><![CDATA[Through baptism we are freed from sin and reborn as children of God and
become members of Christ to take part in the mission of the Church.

                                                                        Adapted from CCC 1213

      We become true children of God at baptism. How do we show
this? We must love one another and show good examples to our

                                                            brothers and sisters at home
                                                            or in our neighborhood.

                                                                   We can participate in
the Church activities like praying for the suffering victims of calamities,
the poor, the hungry and the homeless. We offer a little sacrifice to
share some of our food and clothing to our classmates who are in
need of our help.

      We must try our best to do good to others as young Christians
and true followers of Jesus. We will not quarrel those who bully us
but instead befriend and love them.

      We have the duty to follow the advice of our godparents, love
and respect them just as we do to our parents. Sometimes, since they
are our second parents, they will also scold us when we follow the
wrong direction. But we know this is for our own good.]]></page><page Index="135"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="136"><![CDATA[Renewal of Baptism
                                                            Let us pray:

                                                            Dear Jesus, thank You for the
new life and love You gave me during my baptismal day. Today,

                          please help me as I renew my baptismal promises.

                          Leader: Do you believe in God who made
                          everything? Response: Yes I do believe. Leader: Do
                          you believe in Jesus Christ, son of God? Response:
                          Yes I do believe. Leader: Do you renounce Satan
                          and all his bad works? Response: I do renounce.

      Lord, help me to show to You my best in everyday activities at
home, in school or in community.]]></page><page Index="137"><![CDATA[Lesson

Expected Outcomes:
a. To realize that during the Celebration of the Holy Eucharist, we join

                                                   together as God’s family.
                                                   b. To listen attentively to the Word
                                                   of God during the readings.
                                                   c. To participate attentively and
consciously during the celebration.
Act it Out
      The Grade 2 class will be divided into 2 groups. Show different

scenes of your “Family Reunion”
We recall people who are close to us:

    Every December 26 is a special day for family reunion. Usually the
host family will invite all relatives or people who are close to them.]]></page><page Index="138"><![CDATA[On this event, there are many unforgettable happenings like: the
celebration of the Holy Eucharist together as one family; the
abundance of food and eating together in the same table; sharing of
experiences of the long lost relatives; singing and dancing together.
These are some the many manifestations of our love and togetherness
which make us closer to one another.

    We become united to each other as we lived the life of Jesus
Christ in the spirit of thanksgiving.

                                                     What have you experienced in
                                                     your own family reunion? How
                                                     do you feel after the
celebration?
             When you have a family reunion what is the first and
number one activity that you usually do? What is the most
important activity in your family reunion? Can you remember
other memorable celebration that you shared together as the
family of God?]]></page><page Index="139"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="140"><![CDATA[Everybody wanted to listen to Jesus. He fed many people because
they had nothing to eat. Jesus declared to them that He is the bread
of life. Those who come to Him will never be hungry and those who
believe in Him will never become thirsty.

                                                            The Family of God comes
                                                      together and participates
                                                      actively during the Celebration
                                                      of the Holy Eucharist every
Sunday and holydays of obligation.

      As members of the Catholic Church, we offer our praise and
thanksgiving to Jesus at the Holy Mass. We commemorate the saving
actions of Jesus; His suffering, death and resurrection as a sign of His
great love to all of us.

      At the Liturgy of the Word, we are called to listen to the word of
God taken from the Bible. We believe that it is God who speaks to us.
We actively and consciously respond and sing during the whole
duration of the celebration. When the Gospel is read we all stand and
listen attentively to Jesus speaking to us through the priest. Then the
priest, in his homily, explain and help us understand the words of God
and admonish us to live it in our day to day life.

    The Ten Commandments state what is required in the love of God and love
of neighbor. The first three concern love of God and the other seven love of
neighbor….

                                                                                                    CCC 2067]]></page><page Index="141"><![CDATA[We worship God on
                                                               Sundays or everyday for
                                                               those can. We invite our
parents, brothers and sisters, friends and other members of the Church
to participate in the celebration of the Holy Eucharist in the church, a
place where we worship together as a family of God.

      We give importance to the Eucharistic Celebration because it
is where Jesus Christ offered himself in order to unite us with him.

      During the celebration, the whole church on earth adore God as
our creator and Lord; thank God for His many favors; and ask God to
bestow His blessings on all men. All the Catholics in the world are united
in the same offering with Jesus as our Savior.

      Memorize the prayers we pray at the Celebration of the Holy
                                                          Eucharistic. -In the name of
                                                          the Father…… -Apostles
                                                          Creed -Our Father

                                                          Memorize the responses
      during the Mass: Priest: The Lord is with you. Response: And with
      your Spirit. Priest: This is the Word of the Lord. Response: Thanks be
      to God.]]></page><page Index="142"><![CDATA[To start the Celebration of the
                                                   Holy Mass, we sing an appropriate
                                                   song as the priest, lectors and altar
                                                   servers go to the altar.

    When the lectors read the word of God we listen attentively.

    During the Gospel Reading we stand and after reading we sit and
listen to the homily of the priest.

    During the Holy Communion we receive the Body and Blood of
Christ with reverence.]]></page><page Index="143"><![CDATA[Let us sing together these
                                                               songs:

a. Listen, Listen, listen everyone God is here for you and He is here for
me Listen, listen, listen can’t you hear? His love is here to stay, His love is
ever new.

b. Jesus, Jesus come to me, how I long to receive you Jesus, Jesus in
my heart, be my guest today. Jesus, Jesus come to me, I am ready to
receive you. Come, O Come, O friend my best, never permit to forget
you.

    Till the last breathe of my life ever faithful unto you. Lord Jesus, my
      Savior come to me.

    My Brother be. Lord Jesus, my Savior, be my life, always.]]></page><page Index="144"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="145"><![CDATA[Before they start their lesson, Miss Checada checks the
attendance of the pupils and see to it if all the pupils are in their proper
seats. They are always present in school.

      Some of the pupils in the class of Miss Checada are alert in
answering the questions because they eat enough nutritious food such
as: bread or rice, vegetables and meat. They also drink milk in the
morning before going to school. Others are always sleepy and don’t
participate actively in the class because they don’t eat the right food
needed for their health.

      Miss Checada advises the children to eat their meals regularly so
that they will grow tall, strong, and healthy and can participate in their
school and classroom activities.

      She also reminds her pupils to be generous in sharing some of
their baon especially to the poor.

                                                         What are some

                                                         reminders of Miss

Checada for her pupils? What would you want to share to

the needy if they come and ask food from you? What

happens to us if we cannot eat everyday? What else do

we need in order to live in God’s life? What would you like

to tell Jesus if you do not have enough food to eat?]]></page><page Index="146"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="147"><![CDATA[We need food in order to survive. Food is very important in our life. In
the reading, Jesus reminded us that we should look for food that lasts
forever. Jesus offered himself in the form of bread and wine to nourish
us spiritually. We proclaim that we live in Him.

                                                          Eucharist is Jesus Himself given
                                                          to us to share His life and love.

                                                              At the last supper, Jesus
                               instituted the Sacrament of
the Holy
Eucharist as
a memorial
of His
sacrifice on
the
cross. Jesus
also
commande
d His
Apostles to
always do it
in
remembrance of Him.

      That’s why we always celebrate the Holy Eucharist everyday.
During the Consecration, the bread and wine is turned into Jesus’
Body and Blood.

      The Holy Eucharist is the source and center of our Christian life.
The members of the Church are closely united to one another and to
Christ.]]></page><page Index="148"><![CDATA[The Holy Eucharist is preferably celebrated in the Church with the
assembly of the people of God. The Body of Christ is received during
Holy Communion. When the priest or lay minister says: This is the body
of Christ, we respond Amen. It means, “Yes, I believe” that I am not
receiving the bread but Jesus Christ Himself. We say Amen because
we believe that we are true members of the family of God, who are
formed into one body in the Eucharist.

    ….Those who receive the Eucharist are united more closely to Christ. Through it
Christ unites them to all the faithful in one body, the Church….

       CCC 1396

We receive Jesus and we believe that He is the Bread of Life.

             We always
       desire to live in
       God’s life and in the
       presence of the

Lord.

      In the celebration of the Holy Mass, we are aware that Jesus
offered Himself for us. We see Jesus in the form of bread. This bread is
the “Sacred Host”. That is what we receive in Holy Communion. We
have to prepare ourselves to welcome Jesus into our hearts so that we
can be another bread to others if we follow his examples; making
others happy and by making him known and loved to everyone.]]></page><page Index="149"><![CDATA[Write the missing letters of

                                                          each word. When we go to

M___, we spend special t____ with Jesus. We also show how much we

l___ Him. Jesus invited us to receive His b____ in the Holy Communion.

Eucharist is the sacrament of the b___ and bl___ of Jesus. Only valid

ordained pr__st can consecrate the br__d and w___ so that they

become the Body and Blood of the Lord.

    Anyone who wants to receive Jesus Christ in Communion must be in
the state of grace. One must receive the remission of sin or absolution

                                                       in the sacrament of Penance.

                                                           After receiving Jesus in Holy
                                                       Communion, we have to pray in
silence to thank Him for nourishing and strengthening us spiritually. We
will also respect others as they are in communion with Jesus during the
celebration.

    We will make a habit of visiting Jesus in the church because He is
present there in the Blessed Sacrament. This is one way of showing
our love and gratitude to Jesus our Brother.]]></page><page Index="150"><![CDATA[Let us sing the Our Father with
                                                           faith and conviction.

                               (after the Our Father)
Let us pray:

                                    “Lord, I am not worthy that you should enter
                   under my roof, but only say the word and my
                   soul shall be healed.”]]></page><page Index="151"><![CDATA[Lesson

Expected Outcomes:
                                                   a. To realize that God through the
                                                   priest can forgive our sins.
                                                   b. To express humbly how to

reconcile with one another.
c. To pray the “Act of Contrition” and the Lord’s Prayer before going to

confession.
Describe each picture. Which picture have you experienced most of
the time?Why?

                             The Children are in the library.]]></page><page Index="152"><![CDATA[B.
                                                        The Children are cleaning the
                                                                        campus.

                                                     Which pictures show that they are
living in peace?Why?
Who do you think can give them courage to help in bringing peace to
everyone? How can you have peace? How do you show you are sorry
for the things you had
done? Sometimes we are not at peace because we have fought
with someone. Let us find ways on how to be at peace with
others. Do you want to know more on how to forgive one another?
Listen attentively to the story of the Prodigal son. Be ready to tell what it
reminds us.]]></page><page Index="153"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="154"><![CDATA[God is always ready to forgive us when we do wrong like the
prodigal son in the Gospel. He was forgiven by his father even before
he asked for forgiveness from him. He was willing to make up for his sins.

                                                            God is our loving and
                                                      forgiving Father. He forgives us all
                                                      the sins we committed against
                                                      Him when we ask for forgiveness.
Jesus has given us the gift of forgiveness through the sacrament of
penance. He gives power to His apostles to forgive sins and is handed
on to the priests who represent Christ here on earth. The Sacrament of
Penance is also called the Sacrament of Reconciliation.

One way of asking forgiveness is to pray the

                                      “Act of Contrition”

      O my God. I am sorry for my sins with all my heart. In choosing to
do wrong and failing to do good. I have sinned
against you whom I should love above all things. I firmly
intend, with your help, to do penance, to sin no more, and to avoid
whatever leads me to sin. Our Savior Jesus Christ suffered and died for
us. In his name, my God, have mercy.]]></page><page Index="155"><![CDATA[….Children must go to the sacrament of penance before receiving Holy
Communion for the first time.

                                                                                          CCC 1457

      We are happy when we have many friends. Sometimes
                                                                we hurt others as well as
                                                                God when we are selfish,
                                                                when we
                                                                bully others, or when we

tell lies just to cover our faults. But God is calling us back to Him. He
wants us to be sorry for our sins and confess these to the priest.
Here are the steps to follow when we go to confession:
1. If this is your first time to confess, recall as far as you can

    remember the bad things you did. (If this is your second
    confession, recall the wrong doings things you did from the last
    confession to the present).
1. Tell God how sorry you are.
2. Approach the priest for confession.
3. Do your penance.
4. Try hard not to sin again.

      We commit sin when we make wrongdoings at home, in school or
in our neighborhood. Sin keeps us away from God and from others.]]></page><page Index="156"><![CDATA[As children of God, let us be kind, loving, forgiving and be at
peace to everyone.

      After our sins are forgiven God is happy because we are
                                                      reconciled with Him and
                                                      others.

                                                      Memorize the Act of Contrition
                                                          Before you receive the

sacrament of Penance think about the things you had done which
have offended God and others.

   You should follow the proper way of making a good
confession.

   Have a good examination of Conscience before going to
confession.

    As soon as you are ready to receive the sacrament of penance go
                                                   to the priest for confession:

                                                   -Kneel and make the sign of the
                                                   cross.
    -Tell your sins to the priest.
    -Listen to his advice.
    -Be sorry for your sins and recite the Act of Contrition.
    -Say your penance in your seat.

    After receiving the sacrament of penance, we are reconciled
with God and to one another.]]></page><page Index="157"><![CDATA[Learn this song:
                                                               Father, I have sinned, help

                                                                       me find my way.
                                      Remember not my sin, just let me hear you

                                                                  say.
                                     “I forgive you, I love you, You are mine, take
                                     my hand, Go in peace sin no more beloved

                                                                 one.”

Let us pray or sing:

                         The Lord’s Prayer Let us greet each other a sign of
                         Peace.]]></page><page Index="158"><![CDATA[Lesson

Expected Outcomes:
a. To explain the importance of prayers.
b. To express our gratitude to Jesus through prayer.
c. To pray to God with reverence.

                                       A Good Teacher]]></page><page Index="159"><![CDATA[Miss Grado is an adviser of Grade Two class. She has
thirty five pupils inside the classroom. They are active,
helpful, friendly and obedient. They enjoy in their class activity every
day. They learn to count numbers, read the alphabet and write the big
and small letters of the alphabet on their paper.]]></page><page Index="160"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="161"><![CDATA[Who is the class
                                                     adviser of the
                                                     Grade Two
pupils?Can you describe the pupils? What are the things
that Miss Grado taught to her pupils? Where did Miss
Grado gather the pupils to teach English? What line do
you like in the poem? What happens when you do not
pray? Do you want to know how to start and end our
activity every day? If Miss Grado taught her pupils about
the poem, do you also want to know what Jesus taught
us?]]></page><page Index="162"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="163"><![CDATA[Jesus tells us about His loving and merciful Father. We do not see
Him but He loves us until the end of time. He is always ready to accept
us and helps us through His Son, Jesus to be united with Him in heaven

                                                     someday.

                                                            Prayer is the raising of our
                                                     heart and mind to God. We
                                                     ask Him to provide our needs.
                                                     We say:

            “Our Father who art in heaven, hallowed be
           thy name; Thy kingdom come, thy will be
           done on earth as it is in heaven. Give us
           this day our daily bread, and forgive us our
           trespasses as we forgive those who trespass
           against us. And lead us not into temptation
           but deliver us from evil. Amen.”

      We also pray the Act of Contrition, asking God to forgive us from
our sins. We say:

                  “O my God, I am sorry for my sins with all
           my heart. In choosing to do wrong and failing
           to do good. I have sinned against you whom I
           should love above all things. I firmly intend with
           your help, to do penance, to sin no more and to avoid
           whatever leads me to sin. Our Savior Jesus Christ suffered and
           died for us. In His name, my God, have mercy.”]]></page><page Index="164"><![CDATA[Another short prayer is said after each decade in the rosary.

We say:
                       O my Jesus, forgive us our sins, save us

          from the fire of hell and lead all souls into
          heaven, especially those who are in need of your
          mercy.

    Jesus was praying in a certain place when he had finished praying, his disciples
said to him, “Lord, teach us to pray. They want to pray. By hearing this, the children
learn to pray to the Father.

                                                                                        Adapted from CCC 2601

                                                                      We pray to God
                                                               following the examples of
                                                               Jesus. We raise our voices
to God not only in time of need but also in time of happiness. We also
pray to Him in times of calamities, when we are in sorrow, when we
need reconciliation, when we ask God to forgive our sins. We do not
pray only for ourselves but also for the needs of the other members of
our family and the Church.

                                                          What prayer did Jesus teach
                                                          his apostles? When do we say
                                                          that we are praying? How do
                                                          we pray?]]></page><page Index="165"><![CDATA[Recite the following prayers:
  -Our Father
-Act of Contrition
-O my Jesus . . .

What does Jesus tell us about his Father in heaven? What does the
prayer, “Our Father” tell us? What prayer do we say when we ask for
the gift of forgiveness?

                                                   Tell your parents tonight to pray the
                                                   prayer that Jesus taught us.

                                                   Volunteer to lead in praying the
Holy Rosary at home or in school.

Before going to bed recite the “Act of Contrition”.

      Let us give thanks to the Lord for all the gifts we received
especially for Jesus who taught us how pray. Let’s us hold hands and

                                                           join in singing.

                                                            Ama namin sumasalangit ka
                                                             Sambahin ang Ngalan Mo.
                                                             Mapasaamin ang Kaharian
         Mo Sundin ang Loob Mo dito sa lupa Para nang sa langit.]]></page><page Index="166"><![CDATA[Bigyan Mo kami ngayon ng aming
                                       kakanin sa araw – araw. At patawarin
                                     Mo kami sa aming mga sala. Para nang

                                  pagpapatawad namin – sa nagkakasala sa
                               amin. At huwag Mo kaming ipahintulot sa tukso
                               at iadya Mo kami sa lahat ng masama. Amen.

                              Let us pray:
                                 Jesus thank you for everything. Everyday, you

are guiding us to do good deeds to others. You love us even if we do
not love others especially those who have hurt us. Forgive us as we
forgive one another.

We pray:

      O my God, I am sorry for having offended you. In choosing to do
      wrong . . .]]></page><page Index="167"><![CDATA[Color the drawing.
                           Let us pray the Rosary everyday.]]></page><page Index="168"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="169"><![CDATA[SPECIAL LESSONS

   This unit provide supplementary lessons for the learners which include
seasonal celebrations of the Church: Advent, Christmas, Lent and
Easter. (The teacher may use another supplementary materials.) The
learners are led to increase their love and devotion to the Saints and
Blessed Marie Rivier who intercede for them and help them give honor
and praise to God.

                                                                        The Author

                  Marie Rivier, Woman of Love and Compassion]]></page><page Index="170"><![CDATA[Lesson

Expected
Outcomes:
a. To realize
that God
gave us
angels to
guard us.
b. To show
gratefulness
to God for
protecting us
everyday.
c. To pray to our guardian angel everyday.

               Look at the picture below. Tell something about it.

    Therese and Dom were studying in Talos Elementary School, one
kilometer away from their house. They walked everyday because they
could hardly get transportation. They brought food for their lunch and
went home only after dismissal time in the afternoon.]]></page><page Index="171"><![CDATA[One day, it was raining hard; Therese and Dom were unable to go
home after dismissal. They waited for the rain to stop. It was already
dark when they started going home. While they were on their way,
they heard a noise following them and they did not know what to do.
They were afraid. They talked to each other and they remembered
that their parents advised them to pray to their Guardian Angel.

    So they started to pray by making the sign of the cross and asked
their Guardian Angel to protect and guide them as they journeyed
back home. They reached their home safely. They believed that
somebody is protecting them from evil and harm.

                                                     Why were Therese and Dom

                                                     unable to go home after

                                                     dismissal? What did Therese and

Dom hear on their way home? What did they do while they continued

walking? Who do you think was with them when they prayed?

What happened if they did not pray? Do you know who are Gods’
messengers in the scriptures? Give their names.

Do you believe in Angels?Why?]]></page><page Index="172"><![CDATA[Be attentive to someone who guides us everyday and thank God
for sending us Angels to protect us. We should not be afraid because
Angels are just at our side ready to help and protect us in time of need.

                                                                God made Angels to
                                                         guide, guard, protect, and to
                                                         light our way. We say,

      “Angel of God, my guardian dear
      To whom His love commits me here
      Ever this day be at my side
      To light and guard to rule and guide. Amen.”]]></page><page Index="173"><![CDATA[Another prayer for protection: We say,

      “I sign myself with the sign of the cross+ the sign of victory. I cover
myself with the precious blood of the Lamb. I surround myself with the
light of Jesus Christ. In the name of Jesus, nothing can break this wall of
protection to harm me. Amen.”

The Three O’ Clock Prayer: We say,

      “You died Jesus, but the source of life flowed out for souls and
the ocean of mercy opened up for the whole world. Oh fountain of
life, immeasurable Divine Mercy, cover the whole world and empty
yourself out upon us.

      O Blood and water which flowed out from the Heart of
Jesus, as a fountain of mercy for us, I trust in You.

      Holy God, Holy Mighty One, Holy /Immortal One Have Mercy on
us and the whole world!/ (2x)

      O Jesus king of Mercy, WE TRUST IN YOU.

                                                                   Angels are mentioned in
                                                            the scriptures as God’s
                                                            messenger like Angel
                                                            Gabriel. Sometimes as healer
like Angel Raphael who healed Tobit from blindness and the wife of
Tobiah, Sarah who was possessed by an evil spirits. (Tobit 7-12)
Sometimes too, they are warriors like Angel Michael who fought
against the bad angels.]]></page><page Index="174"><![CDATA[We cannot see them but we feel their protection when we travel
to other places or on our way to school or to the Church.

      Therefore, we will ask Angel Michael for protection from our
enemies, Angel Raphael for healing when we get sick or Angel Gabriel
to guide us when we study our lessons at night and to understand God
message for us everyday.

                                                          Ask for the Angel’s protection
                                                          when you pray:

                                   1. Angel of God

2. Prayer for Protection
3. Three O’clock Prayer

Memorize the other basic prayers:

1. Hail Mary
2. Our Father
3. Act of Contrition

    We pray to our guardian angels to watch us everyday, especially
when we go to school or on our way home after our class.]]></page><page Index="175"><![CDATA[We are safely protected when we pray sincerely the Prayer for
Protection.
We trust Jesus when we pray the 3 0’clock prayers.

At 3 o’clock in the afternoon: we pray, You died Jesus… Before going
home, we recited or sing: Angel of God… Before dismissal or to end our

                                activity we pray and say: I

   sign myself….]]></page><page Index="176"><![CDATA[Lesson

Expected Outcomes:
a. To tell what prayer is.
b. To show respect while praying properly.
c. To pray sincerely the basic prayers.]]></page><page Index="177"><![CDATA[Marina. They were setting at the seashore as he watched the blue sea,
the big waves and the people who were swimming.]]></page><page Index="178"><![CDATA[He enjoyed listening to the roaring of the waves and looking at
the small boys rowing the boat. Then, Micko asked many questions
from his Lola Marina who was just observing him.

      While he was talking, his Lola was very attentive as she listened to
him and sometimes she smiled at Micko. Lola Marina did not get tired
of listening to Micko. Before they went home, Lola Marina described
the wonderful creations made by God. Micko listened attentively to his
Lola while they were walking along the beach.

      Micko did not forget what he heard from his Lola. He was happy
to be with his Lola Marina.

Where did Micko and Lola Marina go? What did Micko saw at the
                                                     beach? What did Lola Marina do
                                                     when Micko was talking? What is
                                                     important for us to do when one is

talking? Do you want to experience talking to someone who loves us

more than anyone else?]]></page><page Index="179"><![CDATA[Jesus was praying in the garden with the three disciples sleeping
under the tree.

    Jesus wants us to be close to Him always. He wants us also to pray
all the time.]]></page><page Index="180"><![CDATA[Prayer is the lifting up of our
                                                     minds and hearts to God. It is a
                                                     loving conversation with God. In
                                                     prayer we concentrate all the
powers of our souls and lift them to God.

      At any moment we can talk to God Almighty in prayer; He has no
hours of appointment; He has no secretaries to stop our entrance into
His presence. It is just like Micko who was talking to his Lola Marina
without any hesitation. His Lola Marina was listening to him attentively.

      God not only permits, but commands us to pray. Prayer is a
privilege and a duty.

      Why do we pray? We pray in order to adore God, expressing to
Him our love and loyalty; to thank Him for His favors; to obtain from Him
the pardon of our sins; and to ask for graces and blessings for
ourselves and others.

    Christian prayer is a covenant relationship between God and man in Christ.
It is the action of God and of man, springing forth from both the Holy Spirit and
ourselves, wholly directed to the Father, in union with the human will of the Son
of God made man.

                                                                                                    CCC 2564]]></page><page Index="181"><![CDATA[It is the heart that
                   prays. Whether prayer is
                   expressed in words or in
                   action it is the whole

person who prays.

      We can pray to God at anytime. We go to a place where we
can talk to God alone. We say our prayers to thank God for His
wonderful creations when we wake up in the morning, or when we
go to bed in the evening. We talk to God before our meals and we
say our thanksgiving prayer after our meals, too.

      It is important to express our faith that we believe in God when we
make the sign of the cross and pray the Glory be. We become closer
to God.

                                                          What is prayer? What do we
                                                          do when we pray? Why do we
                                                          need to pray? Do we need to
have an appointment with God when we

pray? Memorize the basic prayers by heart.]]></page><page Index="182"><![CDATA[We pray when we wake up in the
                                                   morning. We say our prayer before
                                                   going to bed in the evening. We
say our prayer before and after meal. We say our prayers with love and
respect.

      We ask God to bless us and our loved ones. We start our prayer
                                                           by making the sign of the
                                                           cross: In the name of the
                                                           Father and of the Son and

of the Holy Spirit. Amen.

Dear God,
      We thank you for giving us this beautiful world. We thank you also

for giving us our parents, brothers and sisters; and the many people
who helped us grow like our teachers here in Grade two class. Keep
them all in your loving care and protection.

      Thank you dear God for listening to our prayer. We ask this
through Christ our brother. Amen.

  Glory be to the Father and to the Son and to the Holy Spirit. As it was
in the beginning is now and ever shall be world without end. Amen.]]></page><page Index="183"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="184"><![CDATA[Every morning from Monday to Friday, my cousins and I were
happy to go with Tita Anna to visit the farm. The rice and corn were in
bloom almost ready to be harvested. Some gathered firewood and
the others fetched water from the spring. I love harvesting vegetables
and fruits. Then Tita Anna will prepare everything we brought from the
farm to be cooked for lunch.

      During the birthday of Tita Anna, she invited our neighbors for a
little birthday party. Two of those were: Jose who was blind and Maria
who was lame. Maria sang a song while Jose played the guitar. It was
amazing to see the blind man and the lame in their beautiful
presentation of the talents that God had given them.

      Tita Anna and all of us who witnessed the presentation were so
happy. It was such a beautiful and memorable birthday celebration.

      All of us whether you are blind, lame or deaf are gifted with
talents. Our talents should not be kept hidden but they are meant to
be shared to others. We should not be ashamed but happy to share
them.

What did Micah do in the house of her Tita Anna? What did Tita Anna
do during her birthday? How did Jose and Maria make Tita Anna

                                                      happy during her birthday
                                                      celebration?

                                                         Do you want to know another
story of a child who was crippled but it did not stop her to love and
serve Jesus and Mary?]]></page><page Index="185"><![CDATA[It is very clear in the Gospel according to St. Luke that whenever
we have a party, we should invite the poor, the lame, the blind or the
crippled because they cannot repay us. Only the Father in heaven will
pay us for the good deeds we do.

                                                                Marie Rivier was crippled
                                                         since she was a child but was
                                                         miraculously cured because
                                                         Jesus has prepared her for a
greater mission. Jesus invited Marie Rivier to work with Him through
teaching the young and bring them closer to Him.

      Marie Rivier, though her childhood days were full of pains, this
did not hinder her to serve Jesus. In a tender age, she started to
teach catechism to the children in her neighborhood.]]></page><page Index="186"><![CDATA[She had a great trust in the Blessed Virgin Mary to help and cure
her so that she can be of service to Her Son Jesus Christ.

      She also had a great trust in the Divine Providence which led her
to found a Congregation to help her in catechizing the young. In spite
of her frailties, Marie Rivier dared to open the Congregation in the
midst of the French Revolution. Though she was small in size, but her
courage and zeal surmounted the fear that the revolutionists inflicted
on the people.

      Because of her great faith in Mary and the Divine Providence
everything happened according to His will. She was proclaimed
Blessed on May 23 1982. Let us pray to Blessed Marie Rivier to intercede
for all our intentions and of the world.

      Mrs. Rivier loved God and our Blessed lady very much. She knew
that they could do anything to cure her little girl. That is why she would

                                                            carry Marie everyday to the
                                                            church near their house.
                                                            Behind the main altar was a
                                                            big statue of the Pieta,
Mary holding her dead Son Jesus on her lap. Mrs. Rivier, holding her
crippled child in her arm she would pray with all her heart.

      When Marie was already four years old, her mother would leave
her alone in the chapel before the statue to pray by herself. Marie was
never tired of talking to Mama Mary and begged her to cure her.
Mama Mary granted her heart’s desire when she was cured partially
and was able to use her crutches.]]></page><page Index="187"><![CDATA[Marie
was nearly
nine years
old but still
she needed
her crutches.
One morning
that summer
Mrs. Rivier
sent Marie to
the bakery to
buy a loaf of
bread. Marie
had been to
the bakery
before but
this time as
she came out of the shop she slipped on the top step and fell to the
ground. She had hurt her leg once more.

      The doctor could do very little for Marie. That evening Marie’s leg
became worse. Mrs. Rivier turned to our Blessed Lady once more. She
prayed and at the same time rubbed the oil she got from the church.
For two weeks Mrs. Rivier put the oil on Marie’s leg. For two weeks they
both begged our Lady to hear their prayers.

      Our Lady did smile on Marie and her mother for after two weeks
Marie was completely cured. Never again would she need her
crutches. It was a big surprise to the whole village in Montpezat.]]></page><page Index="188"><![CDATA[People would look at Marie walking down the street with her
mother that afternoon and exclaim. “Miracle! Miracle! Little Marie is
cured!”

      Jesus calls us all for a greater service in His kingdom. Jesus was
not choosy but everybody has a place in proclaiming the kingdom
to others.

      What about us? We have no physical defects. We can walk freely.
But sometimes our bad habits can paralyze us from doing good to
others. Sometimes our being lazy or dishonest bring us away from Jesus.
When we bully our classmates, we are not serving and loving Jesus.

We must be good to them.

      As Grade Two pupils, what can we do to serve Jesus in our own
little way? Can we identify some bad habits that paralyzes us in helping
others and in loving Jesus? Can we do something memorable and
edifying during this Lenten Season?

                                                             Praying and meditating the
                                                      Passion of our Lord was one of
                                                      the favorite devotions of Marie
                                                      Rivier.

      Draw the statue of Jesus and Mary where Marie Rivier prayed
everyday to ask for healing.

1. Walk in procession inside the classroom or in the chapel carrying the
                                                   various images or pictures of the
                                                   suffering Jesus Christ.]]></page><page Index="189"><![CDATA[2. Participate in meditating and reflecting the Stations of the
   Cross on Fridays of Lent.

                                                               3. Have time to pray in front
                                                               of the Pieta before going
                                                               home.

                                                                 (Prepare the altar inside
                                 the classroom. Place the
crucifix, big pictures of Mary and Marie Rivier. Ask 2 pupils to light the 2
candles and another pupil to bring the flowers on
the altar.)

Opening Hymn: Mother Rivier, O Mother Rivier Pray for your children all
                 over the world Pray for us dear mother. (Repeat)

Let us pray:

Blessed Marie Rivier, model of living faith, help us to be faithful in
                              following your example. Help us believe and trust
                              Virgin Mary as you did. Help us too, how to follow
                              Jesus Christ by living His words as you did even at
                              your early age. This we ask through Christ, our
                              Lord. Amen.

                              Closing Hymn:

                  We follow Jesus, oh, we follow Jesus, With Virgin Mary and
                       Marie Rivier. We follow Jesus, oh, we follow Jesus, In
                                      making him known and loved.]]></page><page Index="190"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>